<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memorials of worthy persons (lights and ornaments of the Church of England.), the fourth decad. / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
            <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decade 4</title>
            <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B802</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369026</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369026</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187792</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187792)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2842:19b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memorials of worthy persons (lights and ornaments of the Church of England.), the fourth decad. / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
                  <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decade 4</title>
                  <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 104, [8], 135 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. and L. Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
                  <note>Bound and filmed with Wing B790A: Apanthismata. memorials of worthy persons, lights and ornaments of the Church of England, two new decads. Oxford : Printed by A. and L. Lichfield and are to be sold by S. Thomson, 1664.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:1"/>
            <p>MEMORIALS OF WORTHY PERSONS. (Lights and Ornaments OF THE <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fourth Decad.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CL: BARKSDALE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Hi Majores tui ſunt, ſi te illis dignum praſtes.</hi> 
               <bibl>Sen.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:2"/>
            <head>TO Mr <hi>THOMAS SAVAGE,</hi> Eldeſt Son of <hi>THOMAS SAVAGE,</hi> of <hi>Elmeley,</hi> Eſq; AND TO Mr <hi>THOMAS WILLIAMS,</hi> Eldeſt Son of <hi>DAVID WILLIAMS,</hi> of <hi>Corndon,</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving in the late <hi>evil Times</hi> (never to be <hi>forgotten)</hi> been comforted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by the real <hi>Favours</hi> and pious <hi>Munificence</hi> of your Noble <hi>Parents,</hi> I do gladly make this <hi>grateful Remembrance</hi> thereof in the Dedication of this part of my <hi>Memorials of Worthy Perſons</hi> to your Worthy
<pb facs="tcp:187792:3"/> Names. In theſe <hi>Papers,</hi> though it were my <hi>principal deſign</hi> to honour the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the Lights of <hi>our own Church,</hi> yet have I now and then taken in one of the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Genevian</hi> Perſwaſion, thinking They might not be unſociable <hi>here,</hi> whoſe holy Souls, I believe (now that the <hi>Certamina</hi> are ended by death <hi>pulveris exigui jactu)</hi> reſt in peace. Some <hi>Hypereriticks</hi> (who are <hi>pleas'd</hi> with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g but what they do <hi>themſelves,</hi> if yet they do any thing at all:) will <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe</hi> me, and ſay I do <hi>actum agere,</hi> and write what is written already. Truly, as a <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> does not <hi>make,</hi> but frame and compoſe his matter; ſo an Hiſtorical <hi>Collector</hi> performs his Undertaking, when with diligence and judgment he <hi>ſelecteth</hi> and compileth diſperſed pieces for the eaſe and benefit of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>If in this Collection I have done any ſervice to <hi>Young Gentlemen,</hi> and other <hi>ingenuous</hi> Perſons, to incline them more to love <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> to converſe
<pb facs="tcp:187792:3"/> with good <hi>Men</hi> and good <hi>Books,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come loving friends and <hi>Patrons,</hi> or obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſervants and <hi>Miniſters</hi> to the <hi>Church of England;</hi> This is my <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Joy;</hi> This is, to <hi>me,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> or any other <hi>Reward</hi> of my well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meant Endeavours.</p>
            <p>That I have inſcribed upon the <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars,</hi> the names of other friends, is upon the moſt friendly <hi>Plinies</hi> reaſon, <hi>Ingenuum est fateri per quos profeceris.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged Servant, <hi>CL. BARKSDALE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:4"/>
            <head>The Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. Dr</hi> Colet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. Mr</hi> Langley.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III. Biſhop</hi> Morton.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV. Biſhop</hi> Hall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V. Mr</hi> G. Herbert.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI. Sr</hi> Tho: More.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII. Sr</hi> Henry Wotton.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII. Biſhop</hi> Bedel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> M. Ant. de Dom.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X. Mr</hi> Wheelock.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>IOANNES COLETVS</hi> Cum cotis Aomas exculte COLEET Eſorores Te doctos inter poſthuma fama refert.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187792:6"/>
            <head>MEMORIALS. I. Dr <hi>JOHN COLET,</hi> Dean of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Life, Collected by Mr</hi> Tho: Smith <hi>of</hi> Ch: Coll: <hi>from</hi> Eraſmus. D. Anthonio Stratford LL. Bac.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>JOhn</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Coheleth <hi>in the Heb. ſignifies Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes,</hi> the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Colet <hi>is that part of the ring wherein the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtone or ſignet is ſet.</hi> Thomaſ. in voce <hi>pala.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Colet</hi> was born in <hi>London,</hi> the Son of <hi>Henry Colet</hi> (Knight, and twice Lord Major of that City) and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> his Wife, a Matron of very rare Piety and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Fortitude. She had 11 Sons, and as many Daughters of the ſame Husband: all which ſhe ſaw bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187792:7"/> except <hi>John,</hi> her firſt born. Yet, when ſhe was fourſcore and ten years of Age, her countenance was ſo comely and entire, her behaviour ſo cheerful and pleaſant, as if ſhe had never had any ſorrow or any childbearing in her life. So much ſtrength of mind was ſhewen in a woman, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not by Philoſophy or human learning, but by ſincere piety to God and truſt in Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nature was as indulgent to him as fortune; for he had a very proper, tall, handſom and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly body. In his younger daies he much addicted himſelf to the ſtudy of Scholaſtical Philoſophy, exquiſitely learned in the liberal Arts: All <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> works were as familiar to him as his Epiſtles: ſo well read in <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Plotinus,</hi> that when I heard him ſpeak, methought I heard <hi>Plato</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: not ignorant in any part of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Being thus well principled at home (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts) he began to look abroad, and improve his ſtockin forein parts. In <hi>France</hi> he added to his Humanity, what he chought neceſſary for the ſtudy of Divinity: which then he effectually proſecuted in <hi>Italy.</hi> He ſtudied the Fathers and Schoolmen: was well verſed in both Laws: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly read in Hiſtory, both Civil and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical. Modern Writers alſo, he both read and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently imitated, accommodating thereby his ſtile to the Pulpit, and preaching of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:187792:7"/> 4. After his return from <hi>Italy,</hi> he ſtaid not long in <hi>London,</hi> (where his Parents lived) but choſe to live in <hi>Oxford;</hi> where he publickly (yet freely and without ſtipend) expounded S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, being not full thirty years of age, yonger than<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was by two or three months. I here and then I had the happineſs to come firſt acquainted with him. Though at that time he had neither took, nor deſired any degree in Divinity; yet there was no Doctor whatſoever, either of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy or Law, no Abbot nor dignified Perſon in the whole Univerſity, that did not frequent and (which is more) take notes of his Lectures. Which was to be imputed either to <hi>Colet</hi>'s au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or their ſtudiouſneſs and modeſty, chooſe you whether.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But before he left <hi>Oxford,</hi> they honour'd him with the Degree of <hi>Doctor:</hi> which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, rather to pleaſe the Givers than himſelf. From that Univerſity and theſe ſacred Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he was called back to <hi>London</hi> by the favour of K. <hi>Henry</hi> VII. who beſtowed upon him the Deanty of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s: that he might be Preſident of his Colledge, whoſe Epiſtles and learning he loved ſo well: (He was made both Doctor and Dean <hi>An.</hi> 1504.) Of all the Deanries in <hi>Engla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> the higheſt in eſteem, but not of greateſt value: which <hi>Colet</hi> embraced rather as a barthenſom charge, than honour. And therefore, as ſoon as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:187792:8"/> he had regulated his Colledge of Prebends, and raiſed up the antient Diſcipline that was fallen down, he reſolved (which was not uſual in thoſe times) <hi>to preach every Holy day</hi> in his Cathedral, over and above his Sermons at Court, and many other Churches. At S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s he ran over, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a whole Epiſtle, ſometime, a whole Goſpel, the Creed, or the Lords prayer. Whereſoever he preached, he was exceedingly followed, both by the chief Citizens and Courtiers: particularly by Sr <hi>Thomas More</hi> (afterwards Lord Chanc: of <hi>England)</hi> as appears by this following paſſage of his Letter: <hi>What can be more troubleſom to me, than to be deprived of your ſweet company? having been ſo long uſed to enjoy your moſt prudent counſel, to be refreſht with your moſt pleaſant ſocietie, to be rouzed with your moſt grave Sermons, and bettered by your excellent example and life: in a word, in whoſe very countenance and geſture I was wont to be unſpeakablie delighted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Dean's Table, which in former times had, under pretence of good houſe keeping, been too much proſtitute to exceſſe, he reduced to frugality. For he kept himſelf to one meal a day many years together, both before and after his preferment: which at once cut off all his ſupper-gueſts: late Dinners not a few: and the more, becauſe his entertainment (though neat) was neither coſtly nor exceſſive; his ſitting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:187792:8"/> ſhort, and his whole diſcourſe ſuch as pleaſed none but thoſe that were either learned or pious. For ſoon after he had ſaid Grace, his Boy read a Chapter (diſtinctly and aloud) out of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, or <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Proverbs; from which he himſelf, for the moſt part, pickt the ſubject of that meals diſcourſe, asking not onely Scholars, but even ordinary people, if they were ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, what was the meaning of this or that paſſage: with as much ſatisfaction to their minds, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to their bodies. He affected neatneſs in his houſholdſtuff, cloaths, books, meat; but not magnificence: and was ſo much averſe from all filthineſſe, that he could not endure ſoleciſms or barbarous language. He was hugely delighted with the conference of his friends, who oft kept him till late at night: but all his conference was either of literature, or Jeſus Chriſt. If he had no acceptable friend to chat with (for every one did not pleaſe him) his boy did read ſomewhat to him out of godly books. Sometimes he called me to ride abroad with him: and then he was as merry as any man alive: but a good book was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies his Comrade in his journey, and his talk was continually of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whatſoever Revenues accrued unto him by the Church, he entirely committed to his Steward, to be diſtributed and ſpent in houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping. His own hereditary rents and profits
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:187792:9"/> (which were vaſt) he himſelf diſtributed to pious uſes. For, his Father being dead, money flowed in apace from what was left him by inheritance: and leſt that being kept ſhould breed ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe in him, he therewith erected a ſtately new School in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, dedicated to the Holy Child JESUS: whereunto he joyned fair dwellings for two Schoolmaſters, to whom he aſſigned liberal ſtipends, that they might teach <hi>gratis,</hi> but ſo as they ſhould not admit above a certain number (viz. 153. <hi>from Jo.</hi> XXI. 11.) Above the Maſters Chair, ſtands the Holy Child JESUS, curiouſly engraven, in the poſture of one reading a Lecture, with this <hi>Motto,</hi> HEAR HIM: which words I adviſed him to ſet up. And all the young fry, when they come in and go out of School <hi>(beſides their appointed prayers)</hi> ſalute Chriſt with an Hymn <note n="†" place="margin">Which you may read amongst Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus's Epigrams.</note>, Every Claſſe containeth 16. boyes, and the beſt Scholar of each ſits in a ſeat ſomewhat more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent than the reſt, <hi>with the word CAPITANEUS engraven in golden letters over his head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Our quickſighted Dr <hi>Colet</hi> ſaw very well, that the main hope and pillar of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth conſiſts in furniſhing youth with good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, and therefore did he beſtow ſo much care and coſt on this School. Though it ſtood him in and infinite ſum of money to build and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:187792:9"/> endow it, yet he would accept of no partner. One left indeed a Legacie of an 100 pounds ſterling to the ſtructure of it; but <hi>Colet</hi> thinking, that if he took it, <note place="margin">Tam ingentes ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ut ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trapa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deterrere poſſint. <hi>Eraſ.</hi> Ep. ded. ad Cop. Verb. <hi>which book he wrote for the benefit of</hi> Paul<hi>'s School, as he wrote his book called</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes <hi>(at the requeſt of B.</hi> Fiſher) <hi>for Chriſt's Coll. and S.</hi> Johns <hi>in</hi> Cambrige.</note> ſome lay people would chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to themſelves, I know not what authority over the School, did by the permiſſion of the Biſhop beſtow it upon holy Veſtments for the Quire. Yet, though he would ſuffer no lay man to have a finger in the building, he entruſted no Clergy man (not ſo much as the Biſhop, Dean and Chapter of S. <hi>Pauls)</hi> nor any of the Nobility, with the overſight of the Revenues, but ſome married Citizens of honeſt report. When he was asked, why he would do ſo? he anſwered, <hi>That there was nothing certain in human affairs; but he found leaſt corruption in ſuch men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. As all men highly <note place="margin">Morus in Epiſt. ad Col. <hi>Neque valde miror, ſi clariſs. ſcholae tuae rum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pantur invidia. Vident e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, uti ex equo Troj. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dierunt Graeci, qui barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram diruêre Trojam, ſic è tua prodire Schola, qui ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum arguunt &amp; ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt ſtultitiam.</hi>
               </note> eſteemed him for his School; ſo many wondred why he would build ſo ſtately an houſe, within the bounds of the Carthuſian Monaſtery, not far from the Palace at <hi>Richmond:</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:187792:10"/> but he told them, <hi>That he provided that ſeat for himſelf in his old age, when he ſhould be unfit for labours, or broken with diſeaſes, and ſo conſtrained to retire from the ſociety of men.</hi> There he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to philoſophize with two or three eminent friends, among which he was wont to reckon me, but death prevented him. For being few years before his deceaſe viſited thrice with the ſweating ſickneſſe (a diſeaſe which ſeiſed no Country men but <hi>Engliſh)</hi> though he recovered, yet he thereupon grew conſumptive, and ſo dyed. He was buried in the South ſide of the Quire of his own Cathedral, in a low Sepulchre, which he to that end had choſe for himſelf ſome years before, with this inſcription, <hi>JOHN COLET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Somewhat I ſhall adde, firſt of <hi>his Nature,</hi> ſecondly of his paradoxical <hi>Opinions,</hi> and laſtly of <hi>his Afflictions,</hi> wherewith his ingenuous piety was exerciſed: for ſome whereof he might have thanked his own natural temper. For he was of a very high ſpirit, huge impatient of any injury, wonderfully prone to laſcivioufneſſe, luxury and overmuch ſleep, to feaſting and facetiouſneſſe above meaſure (all this he confeſſed to me him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) and he was not wholly ſafe from covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But againſt each of theſe, he fought ſuch <hi>a good fight,</hi> by Philoſophy, Divine Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, watching, faſting and prayer, that he led the whole courſe of his life free from the infections
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:187792:10"/> of this world; and as far as I could any waies gather (by familiarity and much liberal converſe with him) was a pure Virgin to his dying day. All his wealth he diſtributed to pious uſes. He did ſo dayly endeavour to conquer all his paſſions, and ſubdue the haughtineſſe of his mind by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that he would take it well to be admoniſhed even by a child. Laſciviouſneſſe, ſleep and luxury he chaſed away by abſtaining conſtantly from ſupper, by continual ſobriety, indefatigable ſtudy, and holy Conferences. But yet, when there was occaſion, either to diſcourſe with fair Ladies, or jeſt with witty perſons, or feaſt with pleaſant, a man might eaſily perceive ſome footſteps of his nature: which made him, for the moſt part, keep from the ſociety of all lay people, but eſpecially from banquets, to which, when he muſt needs come, he commonly took with him me or ſome learned friend, with whom he diſcourſed in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, that he might avoid idle talk. His cuſtom was to eat onely of one diſh, to content himſelf with one glaſſe of bear or ale, or two at the moſt. And, though he was delighted with good wine, yet he drank very little of it, alwaies ſuſpecting his own ſanguine complexion and inclination, and being wary of all thoſe things, by which he might offend any perſon whatſoever. In all my life I never ſaw a more <hi>happie Wit:</hi> and thence it came that he was exceedingly pleaſed with ſuch Wits
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:187792:11"/> as were like himſelf: but at all times, when he might chuſe his diſcourſe, it was of ſuch things as prepared him for the immortality of a life to come. And when at any time he refreſht himſelf with pleaſant ſtories, he did not fail to make uſe of his Philoſophy in them. He was much pleaſed with the ſimplicity of nature in <hi>little children</hi> (to the imitation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hom we are called by our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour) being wont to compare them to <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. Now for the ſecond particular <hi>his Opinions,</hi> he much differed in them from the Vulgar. The <hi>Scotiſts</hi> (of whoſe acuteneſſe moſt men have an high conceit) he eſteemed heavy fellows, and any thing rather than ingenuous. And yet he had a worſe opinion of <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> than of <hi>Scotus: who,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if he had not been verie arrogant, would never ſo raſhlie (and yet ſo magiſteriallie) have preſumed to define all points of religion: and if he had not ſavoured too much of the ſpirit of the world. he would not have polluted all the doctrine of Chriſt with ſo much of his own prophane Philoſophie.</hi> No man was more a friend to true Chriſtian piety, yet he had little or no kindneſs for Monks, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould ſay for thoſe who are now (for the moſt part falſly) ſo called: and therefore, while he lived, he gave them but little, and when he dyed, nothing: not that he hated their profeſſion, but becauſe he ſaw they did not live according
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:187792:11"/> to it. Yet his deſire was, to have diſengaged himſelf from the world, and betaken himſelf to a Monaſtery, if he could any where have found a Society, that was truly and unanimouſly reſolved upon an Evangelical life. Though he lived very chaſtly himſelf, yet he had a very charitable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe Prieſts and Monks, who had no other crime but venery: not that he did not heartily abhor the ſin, but becauſe he found ſuch men far leſſe miſchieveous than others (if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared) who were haughty, envious, backbiters, hypoctites, vain, unlearned, wholly given to the getting of money and honour. And he was not more averſe to any ſort of men, than ſuch Biſhops, who were Wolves inſtead of Shepherds, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended themſelves by external ſervice of God, ceremonies, benedictions and indulgences to the people, while with all their hearts they ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the world: <hi>i. e.</hi> glory and gain. He was not much diſpleaſed with them, who would not have <hi>images</hi> (either painted or carved, gold or ſilver) worſhipt in Churches: nor with them, who doubted whether a notorious <hi>wicked Prieſt</hi> could conſecrate the Sacrament. Hereby not favouring their error, but expreſſing his indignation againſt ſuch Clergy-men, who by an open bad life gave occaſion to this ſuſpicion. As he did much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of <hi>ſecret confeſſion</hi> (profeſſing that he never had ſo much <hi>comfort</hi> from any thing as that) ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:187792:12"/> he much condemned anxiety in it, and repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He was content to Sacrifice on Sundays and Holy daies, or ſome few daies beſide: either to gain more time for his ſacred ſtudies, and fit himſelf the better for his Pulpit employments, and the buſineſſe of his Cathedral; or, becauſe he found that his <hi>dovotion</hi> had a <hi>greater edge,</hi> when it was ſharpned with intervals: and yet, he would not condemn them who were minded to come to the Lords Table every day. Though he was a very learned man himſelf, yet he did not prize the vaſt and confuſed learning of ſuch as wander among <hi>various</hi> ſciences and books, ſaying, <hi>They got rather a learned ſort of madneſs, than any true incentive to Chriſtian innocence, ſimplicitie and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</hi> He diſſented from innumerable opinions commonly received in the Schools: in which, he would ſometimes tell his mind to his friends, but ſay nothing to others, leſt he ſhould incur a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inconvenience, looſe his own credit, and do them no good, perhaps harm.</p>
            <p n="12">12. And now in the laſt place hear his Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. He never agreed well with his Biſhop, who (to ſay nothing of his manners) was a ſuperſtitious and ſtubborn <hi>Scotiſt.</hi> Neither was the Doctor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to moſt of his own Colledge, becauſe he was very tenacious of regular diſcipline; and the <hi>Prebends</hi> complained, that he uſed them as <hi>Monks:</hi> whereas indeed that Colledge was antiently
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:187792:12"/> called <hi>Eaſt-monaſterie.</hi> The old Biſhop exhibited Articles againſt him to the Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant: That he ſaid, Images were not to be worſhiped,</hi> &amp;c. But the Archbiſhop being well acquainted with <hi>Colet</hi>'s excellencies, inſtead of being his Judge, became his Advocate. Then the old man ſtrove to incenſe the Court againſt him, eſpecially K. <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. himſelf: becauſe the Doctor (when the King was raiſing forces againſt the <hi>French)</hi> had ſaid in a Sermon: <hi>That an unjuſt peace was to be preferred before a moſt juſt war.</hi> Here the King (who was an excellent perſon in his youth) gave an evident proof of his Royal parts, exhorting the <hi>Dean</hi> privately; <hi>To go on in his preaching, freelie to tax the corrupt manners of that age, and not to withdraw his light in thoſe most dark times;</hi> adding, <hi>That he knew very well what incenſed the Biſhops ſo highlie againſt him, and how much good the</hi> Dean <hi>had done by his Divine life and holie Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Church and Nation:</hi> Laſtly, <hi>that he would ſo curb their endeavours, that it ſhould appear to the world, Whoever troubled</hi> Colet <hi>ſhould not eſcape unpuniſht.</hi> Hereupon the Dean humbly thanked the King for his Royal favour, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched him not to do ſo; profeſſing, <hi>That he had rather lay down his preferment, then that any ſhould ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> Again, upon Good-Friday, the Dean made a Sermon to the King and Courtiers, which was much admired, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:187792:13"/> the <hi>victorie of Chriſt:</hi> wherein he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all Chriſtians to fight under the banner of their heavenly King, and overcome, ſaying, <hi>That they, who either through hatred, or ambition, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teouſneſs, do fight with evil men, and ſo kill one another, fight not under the banner of Chriſt, but the Divel;</hi> ſhewing withal. <hi>How hard a thing it is, to die like a Chriſtian: How few go forth to battel free from hatred and covetouſneſſe; and how diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult for ſuch to be in charitie (without which no man ſhall ſee God) who ſheath their ſwords in their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns bowels:</hi> adding, <hi>That they ſhould rather imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their King Chriſt, than Pagan Caeſars and Alexa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ders.</hi> And he had ſo many other ſmart paſſages to this purpoſe, that his Majeſty was ſomewhat afraid, leſt this Sermon would diſhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Soldiers that were liſted. But, when <hi>Colet</hi> came before the King, in his garden at <hi>Greenwich,</hi> the King bids him cover his head, and ſpeak his mind freely: and then his Highneſs began thus, <hi>Dean, be not ſurpriſed with needleſſe fears, I did not ſend for you hither to diſturb your moſt holy labours, which I reſolve to cheriſh as much as I can; but to unlode my conſcience of ſome ſcruples, and to deſire your advice concerning my dutie.</hi> The Conference laſted almoſt an hour and an half, and I muſt not relate it all. Only, his Majeſtie wiſht, <hi>That what the Dean ſpake truly he would ſpeak ſome time or other more plainly,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:187792:13"/> 
               <hi>lest the rude Soldiers ſhould miſunderstand it, as if he had ſaid, That no war is lawful among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> So the King called fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Cup, and drank to him, embraced him moſt kindly, and promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng him all the favours that could be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pected from a moſt loving Prince, diſmiſſed him; and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Courtiers ſaid, <hi>Well, let other men chuſe what Doctors they pleaſe, and make much of them, This man ſhall be my Doctor.</hi> From that day for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward never durſt his enemies trouble <hi>Colet</hi> any more: a perſon, that, in an high fortune and plenty, was led and governed not by his nature, but by Chriſt: in a word, whom I ſhall not doubt to reckon in the Catalogue of my <hi>Saints,</hi> though he be never canonized by any Pope. <hi>Thus far Eraſmus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. I ſhall onely annex a few lines collected out of <hi>Stow</hi>'s <hi>Survey</hi> of <hi>London in fol.</hi> concerning his kindred. His father Sr <hi>Henrie Colet</hi> (ſon to <hi>Robert Colet</hi> of <hi>Wendover</hi> in <hi>Buckinghamſhier,</hi> Eſq.) was buried at <hi>Stepney,</hi> where his Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtill remains. And the Pictures of Sr <hi>Henrie</hi> and his Dame <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ten of his Sons, and ten of his Daughters, remain in the window, on the North ſide of St <hi>Anthonie</hi> (or <hi>Antlin)</hi> his Church near <hi>Budge-row.</hi> But he was born in the Manour of <hi>Hale</hi> in <hi>Buckingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> near <hi>Wendover,</hi> and <hi>Alesburie:</hi> which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:187792:14"/> Manour our Doctor left to <hi>Pauls</hi> School, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of his name dwell there ſtill. See hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Monument</hi> excellently deſcribed by learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mr <hi>Dugdale</hi> in his Hiſtory of St <hi>Paul</hi>'s Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Ob. An. Dom.</hi> 1519. <hi>aet.</hi> 53.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:14"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                        <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:15"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <lg>
                     <l>From a rare Pen there came to fill this Place</l>
                     <l>A Character too rich to sute the Face;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Author</hi> ſaw't<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and (to himselfe best knowne)</l>
                     <l>Admir'd the Love, durst not the Notions owne:</l>
                     <l>And for himselfe, and for his Book, he saies,</l>
                     <l>What's good is Gods, and Gods alone the praise:</l>
                     <l>Sermons take not from mens applause Renowne;</l>
                     <l>The Peoples Practice is the Preachers Crowne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>D: Loggan. delin: et seu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="biography">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:187792:15"/>
            <head>II. Mr <hi>JOHN LANGLY.</hi> Maſter of <hi>Paul</hi>'s School.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Funeral Sermon by Dr</hi> Ed: Reynolds <hi>(now L B. of N.)</hi> M<hi rend="sup">ro</hi>: Markly, Schol. Winche.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>LEarning</hi> is ſo excellent an endowment, that the <hi>Teachers</hi> of it ought to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad in great honour. And I ſcarce know a greater <hi>defect</hi> in this Nation, than the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of ſuch encouragement and maintenance as might render the Calling of a <hi>School-maſter</hi> ſo honourable, as men of great learning might be invited unto that ſervice. Errors in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, are not mended in the ſecond: what is lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in the <hi>School,</hi> is hardly ever fully recovered
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:187792:16"/> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> And by how much the fewer men of great worth and parts are imployed in that Service, by ſo much the more ſhould the loſs of rare and worthy men in that way be bewayled by us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Great was the happineſſe of this <hi>Citie</hi> in this particular, while it enjoyed this <hi>worthy man,</hi> and great the loſſe in being deprived of him. For though, through Gods goodneſs, there be many excellent men remaining, out of whom ſome reparation may be made of ſo great a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; yet ſtill I look on the departure of <hi>this man,</hi> as if the middle and moſt precious ſtone in a rich <hi>Jewel</hi> ſhould drop out, which, though many others remain in, cannot but be greatly miſſed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our dear Brother was a <hi>learned man,</hi> learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the whole Body of Learning: not only an excellent Linguiſt and <hi>Grammarian, Hiſtorian, Coſmographer, Artiſt,</hi> but a moſt judicious <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,</hi> and a great <hi>Antiquarie</hi> in the moſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things of this Nation. Into whatſoever parts of the Land he travelled, he was able to refreſh and to inſtruct his Fellow-travellers in the moſt remarkable particulars of every Country. <hi>Pauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> was not more accurate in the deſcription of <hi>Greece,</hi> than he of <hi>England.</hi> And I have heard, that he had it ſometimes in his thoughts to have publiſhed ſome thing in this kind. He was a man of a ſolid <hi>Judgment:</hi> he alwaies ſpake <hi>è ſulco</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:187792:16"/> 
               <hi>pectoris,</hi> and I have, not without great ſatisfaction, heard him give his Notions upon difficult places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and Arguments of <hi>Divinity</hi> in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diſcourſe, as if he had elaborately ſtudied them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He was able out of his full <hi>Treaſurie</hi> and Storehouſe of Learning, to bring forth both <hi>new and old.</hi> I never knew any learned ſubject ſpoken of in his company, wherein he was not able moſt dextrouſly to deliver his opinion. He was a man of a copious <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> but withal ſo ſolid and judicious, as did ever delight his Audito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, never weary them. As <hi>Livie</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cato, Natum ad id diceres, quodcunque ageret,</hi> we may ſay of him, <hi>Doctum in hoc uno crederes, quodcunque diceret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. He was a <hi>Worker</hi> as well as a <hi>Speaker;</hi> he was not a barren figtree, that had leaves without fruit; nor a tinkling Cymbal, noiſe without love; he taught by <hi>his life</hi> as well as by his learning. <hi>Verbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tantum Philoſophari, non eſt doctoris ſed hiſtrionis,</hi> as he ſaid: and <hi>Dicta factis deficientibus erubeſcunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> And indeed, he was a man of <hi>fixed and reſolved honeſtie,</hi> and wondred in his ſickneſſe, what men did learn <hi>Chriſtianitie</hi> for, if it were not in every condition to practice it, and ado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the profeſſion of it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. He was a <hi>patient man:</hi> patient in his <hi>School;</hi> patient in his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> willingly be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the reproach of Chriſt, and not fearing the wrath of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:187792:17"/> any man, in compariſon of the reverence he did bear to his own conſcience: patient in <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> compoſing himſelf with as unſhaken confidence to dye, as in time of health he would have gone about any other buſineſſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He was <hi>a faithful man,</hi> moſt exactly anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the truſt of his place: <hi>opprimi potius onere officii maluit, quam illud deponere,</hi> as once <hi>Tullie</hi> ſpake. It was hardly poſſible for any friend by any importunity to draw him from a moſt punctual obſervation of timely attendance upon the duties of his <hi>place.</hi> And ſo tenderly fearful was he of miſcarriage herein, and ſo ſenſible of any the leaſt defect, that in a former Sickneſſe he deſired, if he ſhould then have dyed, to have been buried at the <hi>School-door,</hi> in regard he had in his miniſtration there come ſhort of the duties which he owed unto the School. The fulleſt ears of corn <hi>bow</hi> their heads; and the moſt worthy men are moſt <hi>humble,</hi> and apprehenſive of their own failings.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He was a <hi>conſtant man:</hi> punctual and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable from honeſt principles. <hi>Vir rigidae inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiae,</hi> as <hi>Livie</hi> ſaid of <hi>Cato.</hi> He was of <hi>Polemo</hi>'s judgment in this point, <hi>Debere in eſſe quandam moribus contumaciam,</hi> That men having proved all things ſhould hold faſt the beſt, and be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious in goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="9">9. He was a <hi>Wiſe man.</hi> Prudence is requiſite
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:187792:17"/> to tame and calm the wild and unſwaied humors of yong children. It is noted as a ſpecial piece of <hi>Socrates</hi>'s Wiſdom, that he did by his inſtruction fix and reduce the wandring and vitious inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Alcibiades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. I might go on, and inſtance in the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Gravity, Meekneſſe, obſervable in our dear friend, but I only adde his <hi>great care of the School</hi> at his laſt, that there might be an able <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsor</hi> choſen. The evening before he dyed, with great earneſtneſſe he commended it to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany by a Member thereof, who came to viſit him, <hi>That they ſhould uſe their uttermost wiſdom and care to chuſe an able, learned, religious and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox man into the place;</hi> naming <hi>one,</hi> of whoſe fitneſſe both he and the Company and School had had before great experience. And ſo much were they pleaſed to honour the judgment and integrity of this worthy man, that preſently after his death they pitched upon <hi>an excellent learned man,</hi> whom he had ſo providently commended to them.</p>
            <p n="11">11. This worthy friend of mine, the <hi>Friday</hi> and <hi>Saturday</hi> before his own <hi>Fit,</hi> was pleaſed to viſit me, lying at that time under a ſore Fit of the <hi>Stone.</hi> It pleaſed the Lord the MOnday fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing to bring a Fit upon him, and ſending to enquire of his condition, he ſent me word ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was with him, and that he looked on this Fit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:187792:18"/> as a <hi>Meſsenger of death</hi> from God unto him. And though in obedience to Gods appointment, he made uſe of <hi>means,</hi> yet he ſtill inſiſted upon it, <hi>that his time of diſsolution was now come,</hi> and accordingly with great compoſedneſſe and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſſe of ſpirit, waited for death, as a man doth for a <hi>loving friend,</hi> whom he is willing to embrace.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Ob. Septemb.</hi> 1657.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:19"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Reverendus in Cristo pater ac Dominus D. Thomas Dunel menſis</hi> Epiſcopus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Obijt Ano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <list>
                              <item>Aetatis—95</item>
                              <item>Epiſcopatus—44</item>
                              <item>Salutis—1659</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="biography">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:187792:19"/>
            <head>III. Dr <hi>THOMAS MORTON,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dureſme.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Life, Written by Dr</hi> Barwick, <hi>(now) Dean of S.</hi> Pauls. D. Thomae Vyner, Rect. de Staunton.</head>
            <p n="1">1. HIs Coat-armour and <hi>pedigree</hi> ſhew him to be of the ſame Original and Stock, with that eminent Prelate and wiſe Stateſ-man <hi>John Morton,</hi> Lord Chanc: of <hi>England,</hi> and Arch-biſhop of <hi>Cant:</hi> (by whoſe contrivance and management the two Houſes of <hi>York and Lancaster</hi> were united.) But, in his great modeſty and humility, he would not revive, nor ſo much as look upon, a very fair and large deſcent of his Pedigree, when it was preſented to him: though he liberally rewarded the perſon that preſented it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:187792:20"/> 2. The place of his birth was the antient and famous City of <hi>York:</hi> his Parents were of good note, Mr <hi>Richard Morton</hi> Mercer, and Mrs <hi>Eliz: Leedale</hi> (by whom the <hi>Valvaſours</hi> and <hi>Langdales</hi> acknowledge themſelves to be of his kindred:) by whoſe care he was brought up in <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etie and learning,</hi> firſt at <hi>York,</hi> and afterward at <hi>Hallifax</hi> under Mr <hi>Maud:</hi> of whom he alwaies ſpake with great reverence, as a grave man and a good <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oolmaſter.</hi> He took root in the Nurſery of <hi>Hallifax</hi> till the eighteenth year of his age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was tranſ-planted into the Garden of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. An. 1582. he was ſent to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and there admitted into S. <hi>John</hi>'s Coll. wherein were ſo many eminent Schola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s at that time, as he was wont to ſay, <hi>It ſeemed to be a whole Univerſity of it ſelf.</hi> The Maſter of the Colledge was Dr <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker:</hi> his firſt <hi>Tutor</hi> was Mr <hi>Anthony Higgon,</hi> who left him to the care of Mr <hi>Hen: Nelſon,</hi> who lived to ſee his <hi>Pupil</hi> paſſe through all the other Dignities he had in the Church, till he came to be Biſhop of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> and a good many years after.</p>
            <p n="4">4. An. 1590, he took his Degree of <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> having performed all his Exerciſes with great approbation and applauſe. Afterward, for above two years, he continued his ſtudies in the Colledge at his Fathers charge. And then, <hi>Mar:</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:187792:20"/> 17. 1592. he was admitted <hi>Fellow</hi> meerly for his worth againſt eight Competitors for the place. Which he was wont to recount with greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to himſelf, than his advancement to any Dignity he ever enjoyed in the Church. About the ſame time he was choſen <hi>Logic Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> for the Univerſity: which place he diſcharged with as much Art and Diligence, as may appear by his Lectures fairly written, which I find among his papers.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the ſame year he was admitted to the facred Order of <hi>Deacon,</hi> and the next after, of <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> Having received his Commiſſion from God and his Church, he was very ready to aſſiſt others in the way of charity; but not too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to take upon him a particular care of Souls. And accordingly we find him for about five years after this continuing in the Colledge, proſecuting his own private Study, and reading to ſuch yong <hi>Scholars</hi> as were committed to his care and Tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. An. 1598. he took his Degree of <hi>Bachelor in Divinitie.</hi> And about the ſame year, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, inſtituted and inducted to the Rectory of <hi>Long Marſton,</hi> four miles diſtant from his native City of <hi>York,</hi> he betook himſelf wholly to the <hi>Cure of Souls</hi> there committed to him, which he diſcharged with great care and diligence: And yet he did not intermit his higher ſtudies for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:187792:21"/> the general good of the Church while he atren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. To that end he had alwaies ſome Perſon to be his <hi>Aſſiſtant,</hi> whom he knew to be pious and learned.</p>
            <p n="7">7: And this aſſiſtance was the more neceſſary, becauſe his great parts and worth would not ſuffer him to enjoy his privacy in a country-cure. For firſt he was made choice of by the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington,</hi> then Lord Preſident of the North, to be his <hi>Chaplain,</hi> for his dexterity and acuteneſſe in diſputing with the Romiſh <hi>Recuſants:</hi> for it was Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s expreſſe command to him to convince them by Arguments, rather than ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them by force: and this ſhe expreſſed (as his Lordſhop was wont to ſay) in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Nolo mortem peccatoris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. But the Earl dying preſently after, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned again to his privacy at <hi>Marſton:</hi> where he continued not long, before the Lord <hi>Sheffield</hi> (who ſucceeded as Lord Preſident) commanded him to hold a publick <hi>Conference</hi> before his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the Council at the Mannor houſe in <hi>York</hi> with two Romiſh <hi>Recuſants,</hi> then priſoners in the Caſtle; which he performed with great ſatisfaction to the Auditory, among whom were many of the chief <hi>Gentry and Clergy</hi> of York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</p>
            <p n="9">9. An. 1602, began the great <hi>plague</hi> at <hi>York:</hi> at which time he carried himſelf with much
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:187792:21"/> 
               <hi>Heroical Charitie.</hi> For, the poorer ſort being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd to the Peſthouſe, he made it his frequent exerciſe to viſit them with food, both for their <hi>bodies and ſouls.</hi> His chief errand was to inſtruct and comfort them, to pray for them and with them; and to make his coming the more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, he carried uſually a ſack of <hi>proviſion</hi> with him, for thoſe that wanted it. And becauſe he would have no man run any hazard thereby but himſelf, he ſeldom ſuffered any of his ſervants to come near him, but ſadled and unſadled his own horſe, and had a private door made on purpoſe into his houſe and chamber.</p>
            <p n="10">10. An. 1603. he attended the Queens Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador into <hi>Germany,</hi> being deſirous to improve himſelf by ſeeing forein Kingdoms, Churches and Univerſities. His ſtay in thoſe parts was the ſhorter becauſe the Embaſſadors Commiſſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined at the death of the <hi>Queen.</hi> But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he improved his time ſo well, partly in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his own <hi>Librarie</hi> with books at <hi>Frankfurt</hi> and elſewhere, but chiefly in his <hi>converſation</hi> with learned men, and in his forein <hi>Obſervations,</hi> that he alwaies very highly valued that opportunity.</p>
            <p n="11">11. At his return he was ſollicited <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Roger</hi> Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi> to be his domeſtical <hi>Chaplain.</hi> Which proffer he was the more willing to accept, for the privacy he hoped to enjoy in a place where he was not know, for making uſe of that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:187792:22"/> 
               <hi>Treaſure of Books,</hi> he had got in his <hi>travels:</hi> And the rather, becauſe thereby he was brought ſo much nearer <hi>London</hi> than before, whither he muſt have many occaſions to go, for the putting forth of ſuch Books, as he had in deſign to write. For it was not long after that he printed his firſt part of his <hi>Apologia Catholica.</hi> About which time, the Archbiſhop of <hi>York, Toby Matthews</hi> (that moſt exquiſite preacher) conferred upon him a <hi>Prebend</hi> in that Metropolitical Church.</p>
            <p n="12">12. An. 1606. He took the Degree of <hi>Doctor in Divinitie</hi> with the great Approbation of both the profeſſors in Divinity, Dr <hi>John Overal,</hi> that profound Scholar, and Dr <hi>Tho: Playfer</hi> that acute Diſputant and accurate Preacher, who were both of them very competent Judges of mens abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And there began that intimate acquaintance he had with the ſaid Dr <hi>Overal</hi> (afterwards Dean of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Coventry,</hi> and laſtly of <hi>Norwich)</hi> which continued between them till it was diſſolved by death. And about the ſame time he was ſworn <hi>Chaplain in Ordinary</hi> to K. <hi>James,</hi> and by him made <hi>Dean of Glouceſter,</hi> and aſſumed by the Lord Preſident of <hi>Wales</hi> for one of his Majeſties <hi>Council</hi> for the Marches. In his firſt journy to <hi>Glouceſter</hi> he went by <hi>Oxford</hi> at the <hi>Act time:</hi> where he was incorporated and admitted to the ſame Degree he had in <hi>Cambridg:</hi> where alſo he was much taken with the exerciſes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:187792:22"/> of Mr <hi>Dan. Featly,</hi> then a proceeder, and carried great friendſhip to him ever after. At which time (among other eminent Perſons) he fell into acquaintance with that famous Dr <hi>John King,</hi> then Dean of <hi>Ch. Ch.</hi> afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which afterwards grew ſo intimate, that the Biſhop made choice of him to perform the <hi>laſt offices</hi> to him both at his death and burial.</p>
            <p n="13">13. An. 1609. he ſucceeded Dr <hi>George Abbot</hi> in the <hi>Deanry of Wincheſter.</hi> There Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> conferred on him the <hi>Rectorie of Alesford;</hi> and there (among other learned men whoſe friendſhip he much valued) he had intimate acquaintance with Dr <hi>Arthur Lake,</hi> then Maſter of St <hi>Croſs.</hi> In the next year, a Parliament being held, he preached the Sermon to the Convocation, upon Matth: 5. 13. <hi>Vos eſtis ſal terrae,</hi> with general applauſe, and ſhould have been <hi>Prolocutor,</hi> but in modeſty declined it, and preferred a friend of his. In his abode at <hi>London,</hi> he took his lodging at Dean <hi>Overal</hi>'s: who gave him the opportunity of a very early acquaintance with the learned <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> then newly come out of <hi>France,</hi> andentertained by the Dean. The love thus begun was never intermitted in their lives, nor oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by death, as appears by <hi>Caſaubon</hi>'s Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Abby, ſet up at the charge of <hi>Morton.</hi> About the ſame time he had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of entring into a very good acquaintance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:187792:23"/> with ſeveral other eminent <hi>forein Scholars</hi> and Divines: as namely, <hi>Scultetus, Diodati, Du Moulin,</hi> whoſe worth is very well known by their learned works in print.</p>
            <p n="14">14. While he continued in <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain great perſon paſſionately told the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, <hi>That Dr Morton had ſpoiled one of the beſt Deanries in England.</hi> It concerned the Dean to vindicate his good name from that foul and unjuſt aſperſion. And therefore acquainting his Brethren of the <hi>Chapter</hi> with it, they were very forward to give and he not backward to receive a Teſtimonia from them under their hands and ſeals, <hi>That h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had been one of the beſt Deans that ever had been a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Wincheſter in their times:</hi> and ſome of them were very antient.</p>
            <p n="15">15. An. 1616. <hi>July</hi> 7. he was conſecrated <hi>Biſhop of Chaeſter.</hi> While neceſſaries were prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for his journy thither, and for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of his Palace there, he retired himſelf to <hi>Clay-Hall</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> upon the earneſt invitatior of his Noble friend Sr <hi>Chriſtopher Hatton,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there fell ſick of a dangerous Fever, but being happily recovered, preſently put himſelf upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his journy towards his great work, and was me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the borders of his Dioceſs and brought into the City of <hi>Cheſter</hi> by ſuch a great number of Knights and other the beſt <hi>Gent:</hi> of the Country, beſide the <hi>Clergy,</hi> as may give a laſting teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:187792:23"/> to their honour as well as his, in ſhewing ſuch a religious reſpect to their <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. When he was ſetled there, he found all the inconveniences which he fore ſaw, (and which made him at firſt loth to undertake that weighty Office) and ſome alſo which he could not foreſee at ſo great a diſtance. For, beſide the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Romiſh Recuſants,</hi> which hath alwaies been obſerved in this Dioceſs, he found another ſort of Recuſants (better known by the name of <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts)</hi> who, though they were not ſo many in number as the other, yet had they ſo much perverſeneſſe and obſtinacy in them, as made them equal, or rather ſuperiour, in relation to the trouble he had with them. For the reducing of them to their obedience to the Church, he uſed no leſſe fatherly mildneſſe then ſtrength of Argument: and after he had endeavoured their ſatisfaction in a publick Conference with them about the uſe of the <hi>Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. he printed a Relation thereof with ſome enlargements, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>The defence of the three innocent Ceremonies.</hi> But in reducing the other party, the Popiſh Recuſants, God bleſſed him with far better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, to the great content of his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p n="17">17. An. 1617. at the Kings return out of <hi>Scotland</hi> through <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> his Majeſtie was petitioned about ſome innocent <hi>Recreation</hi> for ſervants, and other inferiour perſons, on the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:187792:24"/> 
               <hi>Lords day</hi> and Holy daies, whoſe laborious Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings deprived them of it all other times. The <hi>King</hi> conſulted with the <hi>Biſhop</hi> how he might ſatisfie their deſires without endangering this libertie to be turned into laſciviouſneſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Biſhop preſented to the King in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the next day (Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> attended the King the ſame time) ſeveral <hi>limitations</hi> or reſtrictions, which the King ſo well approved that he ſaid, <hi>He would only alter them from ohe words of a Biſhop to the words of a King:</hi> viz. <hi>That all known Recuſants, and all that are not preſent at Church at the Service of God ſhall be barred from the benefit of this liberty: That theſe Recreations ſhall not be uſed before the end of all divine ſervices for that day: That every perſon ſhould reſort to his own pariſh Church,</hi> &amp;c. The Declaration was publiſhed <hi>May</hi> 24. in the 16. of his Raign: and ſince republiſhed by our late Gracious Soverain, K. <hi>Charles</hi> 1. The good Biſhop, to maintain his hoſpitality in that place, where good houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping is ſo much valued and practiſed, had the <hi>Rectorie</hi> of <hi>Stopford</hi> in <hi>Commendam,</hi> beſtowed on him by the King, where his name and memory is ſtill pretious.</p>
            <p n="18">18. An. 1618. <hi>Mar.</hi> 6. At the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of that great pattern of Epiſcopal perfection, Dr <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes</hi> above mentioned, then Biſhop of <hi>Eli</hi> (who was never known to do the like for any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:187792:24"/> other, and yet did this without his ſeeking or knowledge, <hi>that he might have him his nearer neighbour,</hi> as he ſaid, and of the ſame Province with himſelf:) He was tranſlated to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield,</hi> void by the Tranſlation of his old friend Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi> to <hi>Norwich.</hi> And here his trouble was not ſo great as at <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> though his Dioceſs was longer: becauſe the common ſort of people, for the moſt part, were better principled by the care and vigilance of his Predeceſſor. But yet he abated nothing of his former pains and induſtry, both in Writing, Preaching and conferring with thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t were not wilfully obſtinate: beſides his ordinary <hi>Viſiting</hi> his Dioceſs, and <hi>Confirming</hi> ſuch children as could give an Account of their Faith.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Among the <hi>works of Charitie</hi> performed by this Biſhop, while he was of that See, memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is the Education he beſtowed upon one <hi>George Canner,</hi> (who like another <hi>Didymus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> or <hi>Fiſher</hi> of <hi>Wewminſter</hi> was born blind:) This youth he brought up firſt at School, and afterwards ſent him to <hi>Cambrigde,</hi> where he maintained him, and his Unkle to look to him, in S. <hi>John</hi>'s Coll. After he had taken the Degree of Bachelor of <hi>Arts,</hi> he ſent for him into his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Family, and there inſtructed him in the whole Body of <hi>Divinitie;</hi> then admitted him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſacred <hi>Orders,</hi> placed him in a Cure in <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:187792:25"/> Which Cure the blind man diſcharged di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently and laudably, being a very good preacher, and able alſo to perform the whole <hi>Office</hi> of the Church, as it is preſcribed in the Book of <hi>Common prayer,</hi> only by the ſtrength of his admirable <hi>Memory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. Memorable alſo is that paſſage of the <hi>Boy of Bilſon</hi> near <hi>Woolverhampton,</hi> who being wrought upon by ſome <hi>Romiſh Prieſts,</hi> counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited himſelf to be <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> with a Divel. But the Divel having <hi>ſteeled his heart</hi> (as his own <hi>phraſe</hi> was after his confeſſion) he continued <hi>Demoniac</hi> longer than was intended, and accuſed a neighboring woman, of the Romiſh Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, for bewitching him, ſo cunningly proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the charge, as the woman hardly eſcaped. The <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſuſpecting the <hi>Boy</hi> did but counterfeit, got leave of the <hi>Judges</hi> to have the Boy home with him: where, by his wiſdom and great pains he diſcovered the <hi>impoſture;</hi> and afterwards, upon the Boyes Confeſſion and Repentance, bound him out an Apprentice to a Shomaker in <hi>Briſtol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. An. 1632. He was tranſlated to the See of <hi>Dureſm</hi> (void by the death of Biſhop <hi>Howſon)</hi> a place of greater truſt and honour, as well as of greater emolument. For, beſides the Spiritual and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Affairs (as before) he had now the care and management of all the <hi>tumporal</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:187792:25"/> Affairs within the County Palatine of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> by virtue of the Palatinate, which for many hundreds of years hath been annexed to the Epiſcopal See: in ſo much as it paſſed for a Maxim there: <hi>Quicquid poteſt Rex extra Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patum, potest Epiſcopus intra:</hi> And yet in the ſame he carried himſelf with ſo much <hi>juſtice and equity</hi> for ten years together before theſe late Troubles put a diſturbance in the exerciſe of his Government, that no complaint was ever made againſt him to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> except only the caſe of Mr <hi>Smart,</hi> which yet had no relation to the County Palatine, neither could the charge be made good againſt him.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Some <hi>Rules</hi> which he ſet unto his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were theſe. Firſt, for his <hi>Fines</hi> at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of Leaſes, he never intermeddled in ſetting them himſelf, but referred the buſineſſe to four Gentlemen of the neighbourhood, to make a moderate compoſition between him and his Tenants. 2. In <hi>wreks,</hi> he took ſuch a ſmall ſum of the perſons that had ſuffered them, as was not worthy the name of a Compoſition; and that only to preſerve the right of his place. 3. In <hi>Deodans,</hi> where any man had made himſelf away; though by law the whole eſtate was confiſcated <hi>in deteſtationem criminis,</hi> yet exceeded he not a fourth part of the eſtate after the moſt moderate Valuation. And laſtly, for <hi>Wardſhips;</hi> he uſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:187792:26"/> that tenderneſs, as never any of the Gentry had wrong in their Minority.</p>
            <p n="23">23. How much greater his <hi>Fatherly care</hi> was, for the Spiritual affairs of the Biſhoprick, will appear by his pious indeavours in ſetling com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent <hi>Augmentations</hi> upon the ſmaller Benefices He had given a good ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mple long before, whiles he was Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield,</hi> in abating a good part of his <hi>Fine,</hi> to increaſe the portion of the Vicar of <hi>Pichley</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi> And now in a work of ſo much importance, he applied himſelf for Counſel to three of the moſt learned in the Laws, Lo. Keeper <hi>Coventry,</hi> Mr <hi>Noy,</hi> Sr <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> who all concurred, <hi>That the Biſhops Authoritie over Churches appropriate was neither taken away, nor any way infringed, but that he may now appoint a competent Augmentation,</hi> &amp;c. See the Author.</p>
            <p n="24">24. Having thus fully informed himſelf of his juſt <hi>parts</hi> in a matter of ſo high Concernment for the advancement of Chriſtian Religion, and the good of Souls, he reſolved to put it in <hi>practice,</hi> as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r as God ſhould enable him, and truſt God with the <hi>event.</hi> He began at home with the Pariſh of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop-Auk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and.</hi> Here he augmented the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipend of the Mother-Church from ſixteen pounds <hi>per an:</hi> to fourſcore, and the Chapels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it from about ſix pounds <hi>per an.</hi> to thirty; intending to extend the like Epiſcopal
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:187792:26"/> care in ſome proportion over all the reſt of his Dioceſs: But ſo pious heroical a work became a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortive by the <hi>Scotch Invaſion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="25">25. We are come now to the <hi>precipice</hi> of this Reverend Biſhop's outward ſplendor: though neither his Glory nor Happineſſe incurred the leaſt diminution by his future <hi>ſuffrings.</hi> For he was never more happy in his own thoughts, nor more glorious in the eyes of all good men, then in being exerciſed in thoſe <hi>troubles,</hi> whereof the continual <hi>ſeries</hi> of publick affairs afforded him a perpetual oportunity from this time till his death.</p>
            <p n="26">26. In one of the tumults after the beginning of the long Parliament, this Reverend Biſhop was in extreme hazard of his life by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that were beckned thither by the contrivers of our late miſeries: whereof ſome cryed, <hi>Pull him out of his Coach:</hi> Others, <hi>Nay, he is a good man:</hi> Others, <hi>But for all that he is a Biſhop.</hi> And he hath often ſaid, He believed he ſhould not have eſcaped alive, if a leading man among that <hi>rabble</hi> had not cryed out, <hi>Let him go and hang himſelf.</hi> Upon this and the like violations of the liberty and freedom eſſential to all the Members of Parliament, when the <hi>Twelve Biſhops</hi> (whereof this was one) remonſtrated the juſt fears they were in, and <hi>Proteſted</hi> their diſſent from all Laws which ſhould be enacted, till they might attend
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:187792:27"/> ſervice of the Houſe with freedom and ſaftey They were all charged with high Treaſon by the Houſe of Commons, and committed to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="27">27. Our Biſhop being (after four months) diſcharged from this his firſt impriſonment, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his lodgings in <hi>Dureſm</hi> Houſe, and there attended his <hi>devotions and ſtudy,</hi> till ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time as his Adverſaries thought fit to give him another occaſion to exerciſe his patience under a ſecond Captivity, upon occaſion of baptiſing a Child of the Earl of <hi>Rutland</hi>'s according to the Order of the Church. And in cuſtody he remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſix months before he could obtain his enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. After this he remained in <hi>Dureſm</hi> houſe till he was thrown out thence by the <hi>ſoldiers,</hi> that came to Garriſon it, a little before that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid fact was committed upon the perſon of our late Gracious King: and after that, being impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned by his honorable friends the Earl and Counteſs <hi>Rutland,</hi> he became a part of their care and family at <hi>Exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er-houſe</hi> for ſome ſhort time. But being loth to live at the charge of others, while he was able to ſubſiſt of himſelf, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the air of the Country might better ſuit with his declining years, he betook himſelf to ſojourn firſt with Captain <hi>Saunders</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> and after with Mr <hi>Tho. Rotheram</hi> in <hi>Bedfordſhire,</hi> till by the great civility and earneſt importunity of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:187792:27"/> that Noble young Baronet, Sr <hi>Henry Yelverton,</hi> he went with him to his houſe at <hi>Eaſton-Manduit</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire,</hi> where he found all the tender reſpect and care from the whole family, which a Father could exſpect from his children, till after ſome four months he rendred up his <hi>happy ſoul</hi> into the hands of his Heavenly Father.</p>
            <p n="28">28. When the Houſe of Commons had voted for the diſſolving of Biſhopricks, and ſelling the lands that belonged to them, ſome prevailed for another Vote of <hi>Yearly Allowance</hi> to preſent Biſhops during their lives. Our Biſhop had 8001 <hi>per an.</hi> voted to him: but, while he was able to ſubſiſt without it, never troubled himſelf to look after it. And at laſt, preſſed by neceſſities, having procured a Copy of the <hi>Vote,</hi> found it to contain no more than only that ſuch a <hi>ſum</hi> ſhould be paid, but no mention either <hi>by whom</hi> or <hi>whence.</hi> And by that time he could procure and explanation of the <hi>Order</hi> to make the Penſion payable out of the Revenues of his own Biſhoprick, all the Lands and Revenues of it were ſold or divided among themſelves. Only, by the importunity of his friends he obtained an <hi>Order</hi> to have 1000l out of their <hi>Treaſury</hi> at Gold-ſmiths Hall, with which he paid his debts and purchaſed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Annuity of 200l <hi>per an.</hi> during his life, upon which he ſubſiſted ever ſince.</p>
            <p n="29">29. No man can expect any conſiderable <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:187792:28"/> in the <hi>Will</hi> of a perſon deceaſed, who made his own hands his <hi>Executors,</hi> while he lived: like his great kinſman Arch-biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> who choſe rather to inrich his kindred and ſervants in his life time, then at his death: or rather, like Arch-biſhop <hi>Warham,</hi> ſucceſſor to <hi>Morton,</hi> who lying on his death bed, called for his Steward to let him know what money he had, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding from him, it was but thirty pound, thanked God for it, and ſaid, <hi>He never deſired to dye richer.</hi> Our Biſhop had ſo much left him at his death, that he gave 40l to one of his ſervants who then atten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed him (having provided for the other formerly) and 10<hi rend="sup">l</hi> to the poor of the Pariſh, and his <hi>Chalice</hi> with a Patin double guilt to the <hi>Noble Baronet</hi> for the uſe of his Chapel. The reſt (deducing ſome ſmall remembrances) he ordered for his burial, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h was alſo ſufficient for a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument,</hi> though far below his worth, yet ſutable to his great Modeſty.</p>
            <p n="30">30. I cannot omit the chief Legacy of his <hi>Will</hi> for the common good of ſouls in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> particularly in his own Dioceſs (See it in the <hi>Funeral Sermon)</hi> where he concludes thus <hi>My earneſt exhortation to them is, that they would ſtill continue their former Affections (notwithſtanding all temptations to the contrary) both to the Doctrine, Diſcipline, Government, and Form of Worſhip in this poor afflicted Church: Which, if I did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:187792:28"/> 
               <hi>to be the ſecureſt way for the ſalvation of ſouls, I had not ventured my own upon the ſame bottom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">31. His high eſteem of the <hi>ſacred Liturgie</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> attended him (as I may ſay) to his Grave. For he gave expreſſe command to his Chaplain, not to omit, nor ſo much as tranſpoſe (as he had obſerved too frequently to be done by others) the reading of the <hi>Leſſon</hi> (1 Cor: 15.) which the Church hath preſcribed to be read at the <hi>Grave:</hi> and which being read there, while ſuch a ſpectacle of mortality is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, could not (ſaid he) but have a greater influence upon their ſouls, than any <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon</hi> he had ever heard preached. Great fervor and devotion he ſhewed in the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayers:</hi> whereunto he ſeldom anſwered with a ſingle <hi>Amen;</hi> and at which duty he never kneeled upon a <hi>Cuſhion</hi> (I think) in all his life, nor ever prayed but upon his <hi>knees,</hi> till he was confined to his death bed: and even would neverly with his <hi>Cap</hi> on his head, if he either prayed himſelf, or any other prayed by him, while he had ſtrength to pull it off with his own hands. Great conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he took in the <hi>Church-preparations</hi> for his long home: <hi>viz.</hi> in the profeſſion of his <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>Charitie</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> in receiving the benefit of <hi>Abſolution,</hi> and the <hi>Viaticum</hi> of the Holy Euchariſt.</p>
            <p n="32">32. He lived a great number of years, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:187792:29"/> very few ever husbanded theit time better; for he was <hi>never idle</hi> with his good will. He was often up at his devotion and ſtudy before four a clock, even after he had lived above fourſcore years, and yet very ſeldom went to bed till after ten; and then had alwaies a ſervant to read ſome book to him, till ſuch time as ſleep did ſurprize him: and ſo had he alwaies when he travelled in his Coach, that his journy might not be too great a hinderance to his ſtudy. He uſed to lye on a <hi>ſtraw bed</hi> till he was above fourſcore.</p>
            <p n="33">33. He led his life in a holy and chaſt <hi>celibate.</hi> The iſſue of his brain was numerous, (beſide M. SS.) above twenty ſeveral Volumes in print: ſome of which are theſe that follow: <hi>Apologia Cath. p.</hi> 1. <hi>pars</hi> 2. <hi>The Catholick Appeal. Cauſa Regia. The Grand Impoſture, and proofs. Sermons. Confeſſions out of forein Divines for Biſhops. Gods Providence:</hi> the laſt book he lived to publiſh, a fit Meditation for his declining years in thoſe ſad Times.</p>
            <p n="34">34. <hi>To add ſomewhat of his Character.</hi> 1. His <hi>patience.</hi> In the greateſt tryal of his temper that ever he had, the news of the Vote, that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Church were to be ſold, he only ſaid: <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away; Bleſſed be the name of the Lord:</hi> Which he repeated three times over before the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny he was in, and preſently retired himſelf to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:187792:29"/> his prayers: 2. <hi>His Hoſpitality.</hi> He entertained the King and his Court, and (at leaſt the Officers of) his Army, all at one time in the firſt expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion toward <hi>Scotland,</hi> which coſt him (in that place of great cheapneſſe) above 1500l in one day. There ſeldome came any <hi>Scholar</hi> to him, whether Forein or Engliſh, whom he did not liberally entertain, and diſmiſſe with a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſum of mony. 3. <hi>His Beneficence.</hi> He built a Free School at <hi>Biſhop Aukland,</hi> and endowed it with 24l <hi>per au:</hi> which is more by ſo much than ever he purchaſed to himſelf, for that was juſt nothing. He gave many excellent books to the Colledge where he had his Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the value of 4 or 500l, with an intention at laſt to beſtow 100l <hi>per an.</hi> during his life (had not the times diſabled him) to buy <hi>books of ſpecial worth and not for ſuperfluity.</hi> 4. <hi>His Almſgiving.</hi> While he was ſufferd to enjoy his eſtate, he had his <hi>Beadsmen</hi> in Livery at a conſtant Table, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what he gave away at his Gate, and upon other occaſions. Nay, ſo conſtant was he in this duty, even then when he had hardly ſo much left as to afford bread for his own mouth, that he had alwaies a certain number of poor impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent perſons in a conſtant penſion, that came weekly to him for their allowance, when he was not able himſelf to go among them to give it: and this will be abundantly teſtified by the poor
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:187792:30"/> in all places, where of late he hath lived. 5. <hi>His Devotion.</hi> He would often forgo, ot at leaſt much moderate, his one meal a day; often deny himſelf ſome part of that pittance of time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for ſleep, to riſe out of his bed, and to ſpend in prayer, as the Attendants in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber witneſſe. [See the reſt in the reverend Author of his Life and of his Funeral Sermon.]</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="epitaph">
               <body>
                  <head>Ex Epitaphio.</head>
                  <p>Nullo non dignus Elogio, Eo vero dignior, quod nullo ſe dignum aeſtimaverit.</p>
                  <p>Ob. Crastino S. Mat.</p>
                  <p>Sepult. Feſto S. Mich.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Anno
<list>
                           <item>Salut. 1659.</item>
                           <item>Aetat. 95.</item>
                           <item>Epiſc. 44.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:30"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:31"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Effigies of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> George Herbert: Author of those Sacred Poems called The Temple.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="biography">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:187792:31"/>
            <head>IV. <hi>M. GEORGE HEREBRT.</hi> (Vide Vol. 1.)</head>
            <head type="sub">Out of his Life before his REMAINS. D. Richardo Cooper, Rect. de Weſton.</head>
            <p n="1">1. MR <hi>George Herbert</hi> was extracted out of a Generous, Noble and Antient <hi>Family,</hi> His <hi>Father</hi> was <hi>Richard Herbert</hi> of <hi>Blachehall</hi> in <hi>Montgomery,</hi> Eſq; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the great Sr <hi>Richard Herbert</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> the IV's time; and ſo his <hi>Relation</hi> to the Noble Family of that Name, well kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. His <hi>Mother</hi> was daughter of Sr <hi>Richard Newport</hi> of <hi>Arcoll:</hi> who doubtleſſe was a pious daughter, ſhe was ſo good and godly a Mother. She had <hi>ten children, Job</hi>'s number and <hi>Job</hi>'s diſtinction, ſeven ſons. For whoſe <hi>Education</hi> ſhe went and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:187792:32"/> dwelt in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> to recompence the loſſe of their <hi>Father,</hi> in giving them two <hi>Mothers.</hi> And this great care of hers, this good <hi>Son</hi> of hers ſtudyed to improve and requite, as is ſeen in thoſe many Latin and Greek Verſes, the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious <hi>Parentalia</hi> he made and printed, in her <hi>Memorie:</hi> Which, though they be good, very good, yet (to ſpeak freely of this man I ſo much honour) they be dull or dead in compariſon of his <hi>Temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Poems.</hi> And no marvel: To write thoſe, he made his Ink with water of <hi>Helicon,</hi> but theſe <hi>Inſpirations Prophetical</hi> were diſtilled from above: In thoſe are weak Notions of <hi>Nature;</hi> in theſe raptures of <hi>Grace:</hi> In thoſe he writ fleſh and blood, a frail earthly woman, though a <hi>Mother,</hi> but in theſe he praiſed his Heavenly <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He did thrive ſo well in <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> Coll: that he was firſt choſen <hi>Fellow</hi> there, and afterwards <hi>Orator</hi> of the Univerſity. The Memorials of him left in the Orators book, ſhew how he diſcharged the place: and himſelf inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, <hi>Church p.</hi> 39. That whereas his Birth and Spirit prompted him to Martial Atchievements, <hi>The way that takes the Town,</hi> and not to ſit ſimpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring over a Book; God did often <hi>melt his ſpirit,</hi> and entice him with Academick honour, to be content to wear and <hi>wrap up himſelf in a Gown,</hi> ſo long, till he durſt not put it off, nor retire to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:187792:32"/> any other Calling. However, probably he might, I have heard, (as other Orators) have had a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of States place, being one of the moſt prudent and accompliſht men of his time. I have heard ſober men cenſure him as a man that did not manage his brave parts to his beſt advantage and preferment, but loſt himſelf <hi>in an humble way:</hi> That was the phraſe, I well remember it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This good man like a good genuine ſon of <hi>Levi</hi> (I had like to have ſaid <hi>Melchizedek)</hi> balked all ſecular waies, ſaw neither Father nor Mother, Child nor Brother, birth nor friends (ſave in Chriſt Ieſus) choſe the Lord for his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his ſervice for imployment. And he knew full well what he did, when he received <hi>holy Orders,</hi> as appears by every page of his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Parſon,</hi> and by the Poems called <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and by his unparallel'd Vigilancy, which he uſed ever in his <hi>Pariſh:</hi> which made him <hi>a Peer to the Primitive Saints, and more than a Pattern to his own age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides his Parſonage of <hi>Bemmerton</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> he had alſo a <hi>Prebend</hi> in the Church of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> Which (I think) becauſe he lived far from, and ſo could not attend the duty of that place, he would fain have reſigned to Mr <hi>Ferrer,</hi> and often earneſtly ſued to him to diſcharge him of it. But Mr <hi>Ferrer</hi> wholly refuſed, and diverted or directed his charity (as I take it) to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edefying
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:187792:33"/> of the ruin'd Church of <hi>Leighton,</hi> where the Corps of the Prebend lay. So that the Church of England owes to him (beſides what good may come by his book of the <hi>Country Parſon</hi> towards the repair of us Churchmen in point of Morals) the <hi>Reparation</hi> of a Church material, and erection of that coſtly peece of <hi>Moſaic</hi> or <hi>Solomonic</hi> work, <hi>The Temple:</hi> which floriſhes and ſtands inviolate, when our other Magnificences are deſolate and deſpiſed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He was of a ſingular ſincerity in embracing, and tranſcendent dexterity in defending the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> He that reads Mr <hi>Herbert</hi>'s <hi>Poems</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendingly, ſhall find not only the excellencies of Scripture-Divinity, and choice Paſſages of the <hi>Fathers</hi> bound up in Meeter, but the Doctrine of <hi>Rome</hi> alſo finely and ſtrongly confuted: as in the Poems, <hi>To Saints and Angels,</hi> p. 69. <hi>The Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Church,</hi> 102. <hi>Church militant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As for our Brethren that erred on the right hand, his chief aim was, to win thoſe that diſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked our <hi>Liturgie, Catechiſm,</hi> &amp;c, by the conſtant, reverent, and holy uſe of them. Which, ſurely, had we all imitated, having firſt imprinted the virtue of theſe prayers in our own hearts, and then ſtudied with paſſionate and affectionate ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration, for <hi>voice, geſture,</hi> &amp;c. as in Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to imprint them in the minds of the people,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:187792:33"/> our prayers had been generally as well beloved as they were ſcorned.</p>
            <p n="7">7. There is one thing yet, which I admire above all the reſt. The right managing of the fraternal Duty of <hi>Reproof</hi> is (methinks) one of the moſt difficult <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffices of Chriſtian Prudence. He had not only got the <hi>courage</hi> to do this, but the <hi>art</hi> of doing this aright. There was not a man in his way, be he of what rank he would, that ſpoke awry in order to God, but <hi>he wip'd his mouth</hi> with a modeſt, grave and Chriſtian reproof. His ſingular dexterity in ſweetning this art, thou maiſt ſee in the gua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b and phraſe of his writings. Like a wiſe Maſter-builder, he has fet about a form of ſpeech, transferred it in a figure, as if he was alwaies learning from another mans mouth or pen, and not racking any. And whereas we all of us deſerved the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rpneſſe of reproof, he ſaith, <hi>He does this,</hi> and <hi>He does that:</hi> whereas, poor men, we did no ſuch thing. This dart of his, thus dipped, pierces the Soul.</p>
            <p n="8">8. His Art of <hi>Divine Poetry,</hi> and other polite learning, ſo commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed him to Perſons moſt eminent in their time, that Dr <hi>Dorne</hi> inſcribed to him a paper of Latin Verſes in print; and the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> having tranſlated ſome <hi>Pſalms</hi> into Engliſh Meeter, ſent them with a Dedication prefixed, <hi>To his very good Friend, Mr George Herbert:</hi> thinking, he had kept a true <hi>decorum</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:187792:34"/> in chuſing one ſo fit for the Argument, in reſpect of Divinity and Poetry (the one as the matter, the other as the ſtile) that a better choice he could not make.</p>
            <p n="9">9. I ſhall omit ſeveral excellencies of this Perſon: His conſcientious expence of <hi>Time;</hi> which he ever meaſured by the Pulſe, that <hi>native watch</hi> God has ſet in every of us: his eminent <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Frugality</hi> (the two beſt Purveyors for his <hi>Liberalitie</hi> and <hi>Beneficence:)</hi> his <hi>private faſtings,</hi> his <hi>mortification</hi> of the body; his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Exerciſes thereof, at the ſight or viſit of a <hi>Charnel-houſe,</hi> (where every bone, before the day, riſes up in judgment againſt fleſhly luſt and pride:) at the ſtroke of a <hi>paſſing-bell,</hi> when antient Charity uſed (ſaid he) to run to Church and aſſiſt the dying Chriſtian with prayers and tears (for ſure that was the ground of that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome:) and at all occaſions he could lay hold of poſſibly; which he ſought with the diligence that others ſhun and ſhift them; beſides his care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, not ſcrupulous Obſervation of <hi>appointed Faſts,</hi> Lents and Embers. The neglect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this laſt (he ſaid) had ſuch influx on the Children which the Fathers of the Church did beget at ſuch time, as malignant ſtars are ſaid to have over natural productions.</p>
            <p n="10">10. With <hi>Faſting</hi> he impt his <hi>prayers</hi> both private and publick. His private muſt be left to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:187792:34"/> God, who ſaw them in ſecret: his publick were the morning and evening Sacrifice of the <hi>Church Liturgie.</hi> Which he uſed with conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Devotion, not of Cuſtom, but ſerious judgment, knowing, 1. That the Sophiſm uſed to make people hate them, was a ſolid reaſon to make men of underſtanding love them: namely, <hi>Becauſe taken out of the Maſſe-book:</hi> taken out, but as gold from droſſe, the precious from the vile, The wiſe <hi>Reformers</hi> knew <hi>Rome</hi> would cry, <hi>Schiſm, Schiſm!</hi> and therefore they kept all they could lawfully keep, being loth to give offence (as our bleſſed Saviour, being loth to offend the <hi>Jews</hi> at the great Reformation, kept divers old Elements, and made them new Sacrament and Services, as their frequent Waſhings he turned into one baptiſm, ſome ſervice of the Paſſover into the Lord's Supper:) 2. That the <hi>homelineſſe and ccurſeneſſe,</hi> which alſo was objected, was a a great commendation. The poor <hi>Lambs</hi> of the flock are forty for one grounded Chriſtian; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable muſt be the care of the Church to provide <hi>milk: i. e.</hi> plain and eaſie nouriſhment for them: and ſo had our Church done, hoping that ſtronger Chriſtians, as they abounded in gifts, ſo they had ſuch a ſtore of the grace of charity, as for their weak Brethrens ſakes to be content therewith.</p>
            <p n="11">11. He thought alſo, that a <hi>ſet Liturgie</hi> was of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:187792:35"/> great uſe in reſpect of thoſe without, whether erring Chriſtians, or unbelieving men: that when we had uſed our beſt Arguments againſt their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors or unbelief, we might ſhew them a <hi>Form,</hi> wherein we did, and deſired they would, ſerve Almighty God with us: that we might be able to ſay, <hi>This is our Church, Here would we land you: Thus we belive, See the Creed; Thus we pray, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, Catechiſe, Celebrate the Euchariſt, Marry, Bury, Intreat the Sick,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe, beſide <hi>Unitie,</hi> and other acceſſary benefits, he thought ground ſufficient to bear him out in his practice; wherein he ended his life, calling for the Church-prayers, a while before his death, ſaying, <hi>None to them, None to them!</hi> at once both commending them, and his Soul to God in them, immediately before his diſſolution; as ſome Martyrs did, Mr <hi>Hulliar</hi> by name, Vicar of <hi>Babram,</hi> burnt to death in <hi>Cambridge.</hi> Who having the <hi>Common-prayer</hi> book in his hand, inſtead of a Cenſer, and uſing the prayers as Incenſe, offerd up himſelf as a whole burnt Sacrifice to God. With whom the very <hi>Book</hi> it ſelf ſuffered <hi>Martyrdome;</hi> when fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len out of his conſumed hands, it was, by the Executioners, thrown into the fire, and burnt as an heretical book.</p>
            <p n="12">12. He was, moreover, ſo great a lover of <hi>Church-Muſick,</hi> that he uſually called it, <hi>Heaven upon earth,</hi> and attended it a few daies before his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:187792:35"/> death. But above all, his chief delight was in the Holy Scripture: <hi>One leaf whereof,</hi> he profeſſed, <hi>he would not part with, though he might have the whole world in exchange.</hi> This high eſteem of the <hi>Word of Life,</hi> as it wrought in himſelf a wondrous expreſſion of high Reverence, when ever he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther read it himſelf, or heard others read it; ſo it made him equally wonder, that thoſe who pretended ſuch extraordinary <hi>love to Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as many did, could poſſibly give ſuch leave and liberty to themſelves, as to hear <hi>that Word,</hi> that ſhall judge us at the laſt day, without any the leaſt expreſſion of that <hi>holy fear</hi> and trembling, which they ought to charge upon their Souls in private, and in publick to imprint upon others.</p>
            <p n="13">13. I have not ſo much as with one daſh of a pencil offered to deſcribe that <hi>perſon</hi> of his, which afforded ſo unuſual a <hi>Conteſſeration</hi> of Elegancies, and <hi>Set</hi> of rarities to the beholder: nor ſaid I any thing of his perſonal <hi>Relation,</hi> as a Husband to a loving and virtuous Lady, as a Kinſman, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp;c. Yet will I not ſilence his ſpiritual love and cate of <hi>Servants,</hi> teaching Maſters this duty; To allow their ſervants dayly time wherein to pray privately, and to enjoyn them to do it; holding this for true generally: <hi>That publick prayer alone to ſuch perſons, is no prayer at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. I have given thee only theſe lineaments
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:187792:36"/> of his mind, and thou mayeſt fully ſerve thy ſelf of his book, <hi>The Country-Parſon,</hi> in what vertue of his thy ſoul longeth after. <hi>His practice</hi> it was, and <hi>his Character</hi> it is: His, as <hi>Author;</hi> and his, as <hi>Object.</hi> Yet, lo, the <hi>Humilitie</hi> of this gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man! He had ſmall eſteem of this book, and but very little of his Poems. Though God had magnifyed him with extraordinary Gifts, yet ſaid he, <hi>God hath broken into my ſtudy, and taken off my Chariot wheels: I have nothing worthy of God:</hi> And even this lowlineſſe in his own eyes, doth more advance their worth, and his Virtues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Here, my Reader, give me leave to propoſe to thy view ſome lines of that excellent Figure,</hi> The Country Parſon, <hi>written by the Author</hi> 1632. <hi>printed</hi> 1652. <hi>which book I read with joy that we have any ſuch, and with grief that we have no more.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Country Parſon</hi> is exceeding exact in his <hi>life,</hi> being holy, juſt, prudent, temperate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old, grave in all his waies. And becauſe the two higheſt points of life, wherein a Chriſtian is moſt ſeen, are Patience and Mortification: Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in regard of Afflictions, Mortification in regard of luſts and affections, and the ſtupifying and deading of all the clamorous powers of the ſoul, therefore he hath throughly ſtudied theſe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:187792:36"/> that he may be an abſolute maſter and commander of himſelf for all the purpoſes which God hath ordained him. Yet in theſe points he labours moſt in thoſe things which are moſt apt to ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize his Pariſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He is full of all <hi>knowledge.</hi> They ſay it is an ill Maſon that refuſeth any ſtone: and there is no knowledge, but in a skilful hand ſerves ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſitively as it is, or elſe to illuſtrate ſome other knowledge. He condiſcends even to the knowledge of tillage and paſtorage, and makes great uſe of them in teaching; becauſe people, by what they underſtand, are beſt led to what they underſtand not. But the chief and top of his knowledge conſiſts in the book of books, the ſtorehouſe and magazene of life and comfort, the holy Scriptures. There he ſucks, and lives. There he finds four things: Precepts for life, Doctrines for knowledg, Examples for illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and promiſes for comforts: Theſe he hath dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted ſeverally. And for the underſtanding of theſe, the means he uſeth are, a holy life, prayer, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He hath read the <hi>Fathers</hi> alſo, and the Schoolmen, and the later Writers, or a good proportion of all: out of all which he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a book, and Body of Divinity, which is the ſtorehouſe of his Sermons, and which he preacheth all his life; but diverſly clothed, illuſtrated and enlarged. For, though the world is full of ſuch
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:187792:37"/> compoſures, yet every mans own is fitteſt, readieſt, and moſt ſavo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry to him. Beſides, this being to be done in his yonger and preparatory times, it is an honeſt joy ever after to look upon his well-ſpent hours. This Body he made by way of expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church-Catechiſm, to which all Divinity m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y eaſily be reduced. For it being indifferent in it ſelf to chooſe any method, that is be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to be choſen, of which there is likelieſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be moſt uſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When he is to read <hi>Divine Services,</hi> he compoſeth himſelf to all poſſible Reverence, as being truly touched with the Majeſty of God, and that being firſt affected himſelf he may affect alſo his people; kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, that no Sermon moves them ſo much to a reverence, which they forget again when they come to pray, as a devout beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the very act of praying. Accordingly, his voice is humble, his words treatable, and ſlow; yet not ſo ſlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neither, as to let the fervency of the ſupplicant hang and dye between ſpeaking; but with a more livelineſs between fear and zeal, pauzing yet preſſing, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ms his duty. Beſides his example, he having often inſtructed his people how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Divine Service, exacts of them all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reverence, by no means enduring either talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or ſleeping, or gazing, or leaning, or half-kneeling, or any undutiful behaviour in them; but cauſing them, when they ſit, or ſtand, or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:187792:37"/> kneel, to do all in a ſtrait and ſteady poſture, as attending to what is done in the Church; and every one, man and child anſwering aloud both <hi>Amen,</hi> and all other anſwers on the peoples parts, uſing their reaſon, and applying their powers to the Service of God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He <hi>preacheth</hi> conſtantly: the Pulpit is his joy and his Throne. If he at any time intermit, it is either for want of health, or againſt ſome great Feſtival, that he may the better celebrate it; or for the variety of the hearers, that he may be heard, at his return more attentively. When he intermits, he is ever well ſupplyed by ſome able man, who treads in his ſteps, and will not throw down what he hath built; whom alſo he intreats to preſſe ſome point, that he himſelf hath often urged with no great ſucceſſe, that ſo in the mouth of two or three witneſſes the truth may be the more eſtabliſhed. When he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he procures attention with all poſſible art, both by earneſtneſs of ſpeech (it being natural for men to think, that where is much earneſtneſs, there is ſomething worth hearing) and by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and buſie caſt of his eye on his Auditors, with letting them know, that he obſerves who marks, and who not; and with particularizing of his ſpeech, now to the younger ſort, then to the elder, now to the poor, and now to the rich. This is for you, and This is for you: for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:187792:38"/> ever touch, and awake, more than generals. He exceeds not an hour in preaching, becauſe all ages have thought that a competency, and he that profits not in that time, will leſs afterwards; the ſame affection which made him not profit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, making him then weary; and ſo he grows from not reliſhing, to loathing.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>On Sundaies,</hi> having read Divine Service twice fully, and Preached in the morning, and Catechized in the afternoon, he thinks he hath in ſome meaſure, according to poor and frail man, diſcharged the publick duties of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The reſt of the duty he ſpends either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling neighbours that are at variance, or in viſiting the ſick, or in exhortaton to ſome of his flock by themſelves, whom his Sermons cannot or do not reach. And every one is more awaked, when we come and ſay, Thou art the man. At night he thinks it a very fit time, both ſutable to the joy of the day, and without hinderance to publick duties, either to entertain ſome of his neighbours, or to be entertained of them: where he takes occaſion to diſcourſe of ſuch things as are both profitable and pleaſant, and to raiſe up their minds to apprehend God's bleſſing to our Church and State, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:187792:38"/>
            <p> (Here I had ended, but ſince I ſee the Book is hard in come by, prithee take ſome more.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <hi>Country Parſon</hi> conſidering that <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> is a higher ſtate than Matrimony, and that the <hi>Miniſtrie</hi> requires the beſt and higheſt things, is rather unmarried, than married. But yet as the temper of his <hi>bodie</hi> may be, or as the temper of his <hi>Pariſh</hi> may be where he may have occaſion to converſe with women, and that among ſuſpicious men, and other like circumſtances con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, he is rather married than unmarried. Let him communicate the thing often by <hi>prayer</hi> to to God, and as his <hi>grace</hi> ſhall direct him, ſo let him proceed. If he be unmarried, and keep houſe, he hath not <hi>a woman</hi> in his houſe, but finds oppertunities of having his meat dreſt and other ſervices done by men ſervants at home, and his linnen waſhed abroad. If he be unmarried and ſojourn, he never talks with any woman <hi>alone,</hi> but in the audience of others, and that ſeldom, and then alſo in a ſerious manner, never <hi>jestingly</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſportfully. He is very <hi>circumſpect</hi> in all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, both of his behaviour, ſpeech and very looks, knowing himſelf to be both ſuſpected and envied. If he be married, the <hi>choice</hi> of his wife was made rather by his <hi>ear,</hi> than by his <hi>eye:</hi> his judgment, not his affection found out a fit wife for him;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:187792:39"/> whoſe humble and liberal diſpoſition he preferred before beauty, riches or honour.</p>
            <p n="8">8. He is very exact in the <hi>government of his houſe,</hi> making it a copy and model for his Pariſh. He knows the temper and pulſe of every perſon in his houſe, and accordingly either meets with their vices, or advanceth their virtues. His <hi>wife</hi> is either religious, or night and day he is winning her to it. Inſtead of the qualities of the world, he requires only three of her. 1. a training up of her <hi>children</hi> and maids in the fear of God, with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and catechiſing, and all religious duties, 2. a curing and healing of all <hi>wounds</hi> and ſores with her own hands: which skill either ſhe brought with her, or he takes care ſhe ſhall learn it of ſome religious neighbour, 3. a providing for her <hi>family</hi> in ſuch ſort, as that neither they want a competent ſuſtentation, nor her husband in debt. His <hi>children</hi> he firſt makes Chriſtians, and then Common-wealths men: the one he owes to his heavenly Country, the other to his earthly, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no title to either, except he do good to both. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>ſervants</hi> are all religious: and were it not his <hi>duty</hi> to have them ſo, it were his <hi>profit:</hi> for none are ſo well ſerved, as by religious ſervants, both becauſe they do beſt, and becauſe what they do is bleſſed and proſpers.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Owing a debt of <hi>Charitie</hi> to the poor, and of <hi>courteſie</hi> to his other Pariſhioners, he ſo diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:187792:39"/> that he keeps his mony for the poor, and his table for thoſe that be above his alms. Not, but that the <hi>poor</hi> are welcome alſo to his table: whom he ſometimes purpoſely takes home with him, ſetting them cloſe by him, and carving for them, both for his own humility and their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, who are much cheered with ſuch friendlineſs. But he chooſeth rather to give the poor <hi>money,</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h they can employ to their advantage, and ſutably to their needs.</p>
            <p n="10">10. He is full of <hi>Charitie:</hi> it is his predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant element: all his works relliſh of Charity. When he riſeth in the morning, he bethinketh himſelf what <hi>good deeds</hi> he can do that day, and preſently doth them; counting that day loſt, wherein he hath not exerciſed his charity. He takes care, that there be not a <hi>begger,</hi> or idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in his pariſh, but that all be in a competent way of getting their living. When-ever he gives any thing, and ſees them labour in thanking of him, he exacts of them to let him alone, and ſay rather, <hi>God be glorified:</hi> that ſo the thanks may go the right way, and thither only, where th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are only due. So doth he alſo, before giving, make them ſay their <hi>prayers</hi> firſt, or the <hi>Creed,</hi> and <hi>ten Commandements;</hi> and as he finds them perfect, rewards them the more. For other <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings</hi> are <hi>lay</hi> and ſecular, but this is to give like a <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:187792:40"/> 11. He hath a ſpecial care of his <hi>Church,</hi> that all things there be decent, and befitting his name by which it is called. Therefore, 1. he takes order that all things be in good <hi>repair.</hi> 2. That the Church be ſwept and kept <hi>clean</hi> without duſt or cobwebs, and at great Feſtivals ſtrawed and ſtuck with boughs, and perfumed with incenſe. 3. That there be fit and proper texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> every where painted, and that all the painting be grave and reverend, not with light colours or fooliſh anticks. 4. That all the <hi>books</hi> appointed by Authority be there, and thoſe not torn or fouled, but whole and clean and well bound, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Upon the afternoons in the week daies, he takes occaſion ſometimes <hi>to viſit</hi> in perſon, now one quarter of his pariſh, now another. For there he ſhall find his flock moſt naturally as they are, <hi>wallowing</hi> in the midſt of their affairs: whereas on <hi>Sondaies</hi> it is eaſie for them to compoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to order, which they put on as their Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-cloths, and come to Church in frame, but commonly the next day put off both. When he comes to any houſe, firſt he <hi>bleſſeth</hi> it, and then as he finds the perſons of the houſe imployed, ſo he forms his diſcourſe. Thoſe that he finds <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly</hi> employed, he commends them much and furthers them, by furniſhing them with good books. Thoſe that he finds buſie in the works of their <hi>calling,</hi> he commendeth them alſo. For it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:187792:40"/> is a good and juſt thing for every one to do their own buſineſſe. But then he admoniſheth them of two things. 1. That they dive not too deep into <hi>worldly affairs,</hi> plunging themſelves over head and ears into carkino and caring; but that they labour ſo, as neither to labour <hi>anxiouſly,</hi> nor <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfully,</hi> nor <hi>profanely.</hi> 2. He adviſeth them ſo to labour for <hi>wealth</hi> and maintenance, as that they make not that the end of their labour, but that they may have wherewithal to ſerve God the better, and to do good deeds. The <hi>Parſon</hi> alſo queſtions what <hi>order</hi> is kept in the <hi>houſe,</hi> as about <hi>prayers morning and evening</hi> on their knees, <hi>reading</hi> of Scripture, <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> &amp;c. Neither diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he to enter into the <hi>pooreſt Cottage,</hi> though he even creep into it, and though it ſmell never ſo lothſomely. For, <hi>both God is there alſo, and thoſe for whom God dyed:</hi> and ſo much the rather doth he ſo, as his acceſſe to the <hi>poor</hi> is more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then to the <hi>rich:</hi> and in regard of himſelf it is more <hi>humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. When any of his Cure is <hi>ſick</hi> or <hi>afflicted</hi> wih loſſe of friend, or eſtate, or any waies di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, he fails not to afford his beſt <hi>comforts,</hi> and rather goes to them, then ſends for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, though they can, and otherwiſe ought to come to him. To this end he hath throughly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted all the points of <hi>Conſolation,</hi> as having continual uſe of them: ſuch as are, from God's
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:187792:41"/> general <hi>providence</hi> extended even to Lillies, from his particular to his <hi>Church,</hi> from his <hi>promiſes,</hi> from the <hi>examples</hi> of all Saints that ever were, from <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf perfecting our Redemption no other way then by ſorrow, from the <hi>benefit</hi> of affliction which ſoftens and works the ſtubborn heart of man, from the certainty both of <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and reward</hi> if we faint not, from the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon</hi> of the moment of griefs here, with the weight of joyes hereafter.</p>
            <p n="14">14. When a juſt occaſion calleth him <hi>out of his Pariſh</hi> (which he diligently and ſtrictly weigheth, his Pariſh being all his joy and thought) he leaveth not his Miniſtry behind him, but is <hi>himſelf</hi> wherever he is. Therefore thoſe he meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the way he <hi>bleſſeth</hi> audibly, and with thoſe he overtakes, or that overtake him, he begins <hi>good diſcourſes,</hi> ſuch as may edifie, interpoſing ſometimes ſome ſhort and honeſt <hi>refreſhments,</hi> which may make his other diſcourſes more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and leſſe tedious. And when he comes to his <hi>Inne,</hi> he refuſeth not to joyn in <hi>prayer,</hi> that he may <hi>enlarge</hi> the glory of God to the company he is in. The like he doth in the morning, uſing pleaſantly the Outlandiſh Proverb: <hi>Prayers and Provinder never hinder journy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Wherever he is, he keeps <hi>God's watch,</hi> that is, there is nothing ſpoken or done in the company where he is, but comes under his teſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:187792:41"/> and cenſure: If it be <hi>well</hi> ſpoken or done, he takes an occaſion to commend and enlarge it; if <hi>ill,</hi> he preſently laies hold of it, leſt the <hi>poyſon</hi> ſteal into ſome young and unwary ſpirits, and poſſeſſe them even before they themſelves heed it. But this he doth diſcreerly, with mollifying and ſuppling words: <hi>This was not ſo well ſaid, as it might have been forborn; We cannot allow this.</hi> Or elſe, if the thing will admit Interpretation, <hi>Your meaning is not thus, but thus,</hi> or, <hi>So far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed what you ſaid is true, and well ſaid; but this will not ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. He is <hi>in God's ſtead</hi> to his Pariſh, and diſchargeth God what he can of his promiſes. Wherefore there is nothing done well, whereof he is not the <hi>rewarder.</hi> If he chance to find any reading in another's <hi>Bible,</hi> he provides him one of his own. If he find another giving a poor man a <hi>penny,</hi> he gives him a <hi>teſter</hi> for it, if the giver be fit to receive it: if he be of a condition above ſuch gifts, he ſends him a good <hi>book,</hi> or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeth him in his <hi>Tiths,</hi> telling him when he hath forgotten it, <hi>This I do, becauſe at ſuch and ſuch a time you were charitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. The <hi>Country Parſon</hi> values <hi>Catechizing</hi> highly. He uſeth and prefereth the ordinary <hi>Church-Catechiſm,</hi> partly for <hi>obodience</hi> to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, partly for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> ſake, that the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me common truths may be every where profeſſed.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:187792:42"/> He requires <hi>all</hi> to be preſent at Catechizing. 1. For the <hi>authority</hi> of the work. 2. That Parents and Maſters, as they hear the Anſwers prove, may, when they come home, either <hi>commend</hi> or <hi>reprove,</hi> either reward or puniſh. 3. That thoſe of the <hi>elder ſort,</hi> who are not well grounded, may then, by an honourable way, take occaſion to be better inſtructed. 4. That thoſe who are well gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the knowledge of religion, may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their grounds, <hi>renew their vows,</hi> and by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of both enlarge their meditations.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Being to adminiſter the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> he is at a ſtand with himſelf, how or what behaviour to aſſume for ſo holy things. At <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> being himſelf in <hi>white,</hi> he requires the preſence of all, and baptizeth, not willingly, but on Sondaies, or great daies. He admits no vain or idle <hi>names,</hi> but ſuch as are uſual and accuſtomed. He ſaies that prayer with great devotion, where God is thanked <hi>for calling us to the knowledge of his grace:</hi> willingly and cheerfully <hi>croſſeth</hi> the child, and thinketh the Ceremony not only innocent, but reverend: inſtructeth the <hi>Godfathers</hi> and <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers,</hi> that it is no complemental and light thing to ſuſtain that place: adviſeth <hi>all</hi> to call to mind their Baptiſm often. At the times of the <hi>Holy Communion,</hi> he firſt takes order with the <hi>Church-wardens,</hi> that the Elements be of the <hi>beſt,</hi> not cheap or courſe, much leſſe ill-taſted or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſom.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:187792:42"/> Secondly, he conſiders and looks into the <hi>ignorance or careleſneſſe</hi> of his flock, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly applies himſelf with Catechizing and lively Exhortations, not on the Sonday of the Communion only (for then it is too late) but the Sonday or Sondays before the Communion, or on the <hi>Eves</hi> of all thoſe daies.</p>
            <p n="18">18. If there be any of his Pariſh that hold <hi>strange doctrines,</hi> he uſes all poſſible diligence to reduce them to the <hi>common faith.</hi> The firſt me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns he uſeth is <hi>prayer,</hi> beſeeching the <hi>Father of lights to open their eyes:</hi> the ſecond is a <hi>loving and ſweet uſage</hi> of them: the third is the obſervation, what is the main <hi>pillar</hi> of their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe, whereon they rely; as, if he be a Papiſt, the <hi>Church</hi> is the hinge he turns on; if a Schiſmatick <hi>ſcandal.</hi> Theſe he hath diligently examined, &amp;c. <hi>Vide Auctorem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="biography">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:187792:43"/>
            <head>V. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>JOSEPH HALL,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi> (See Vol. 1.)</head>
            <head type="sub">Out of his Life, written with his own hand. D. Arthuro Charlett, Rect. de Colinb.</head>
            <figure>
               <lg>
                  <l>How farre beyond a Picture is his worth</l>
                  <l>Whome Pen, nor Pencill truly can ſett forth!</l>
                  <l>Behold his Reuerend FACE his better PART</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s left vngrau'd, this was beyond all Art.</l>
                  <l>His holy Thoughts in sacred MEDITATIONS</l>
                  <l>His rauisht SOVLE w<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. heauenly CONTEMPLATIONS</l>
                  <l>Could not bee drawne. Heere onely are his Lookes</l>
                  <l>The Pictures of the rest are in his BOOKES.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sampſon</p>
               <p>Imprinted for Philemon Stephens &amp; Christopher Meredith. 1628.</p>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>VERA EFFIGIES REVERENDI DO<hi rend="sup">NI</hi>. IOSEPHI HALL N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>RWICI EPISCOPI.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Picture repreſents the <hi>Forme,</hi> where dwells</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Mind,</hi> which nothing but that <hi>Mind</hi> excells.</l>
                  <l>There's <hi>Wiſdome, Learning. Witt;</hi> there <hi>Grace</hi> &amp; <hi>Love</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rule over all the rest: enough to prove,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the froward <hi>Conſcience</hi> of this <hi>Time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Reverend <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>BISHOP</hi> is no <hi>Crime.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </figure>
            <p n="2">2. My parents had from my Infancy devoted me to this <hi>Sacred Calling,</hi> whereto, by the bleſſing of God, I have ſeaſonably attained: for this cauſe, I was trained up in the publick <hi>School</hi> of the place. After I had ſpent ſome years (not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether indiligently) under the ferule of ſuch <hi>Maſters</hi> as the place afforded, and had near at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to ſome competent ripeneſſe for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie,</hi> my School-maſter perſwaded my Father that I might have my Education under an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Divine,</hi> the Preacher of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi> About which time, my <hi>elder brother</hi> having ſome occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to journy into <hi>Cambridge,</hi> was kindly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained there by Mr <hi>Nath: Gilby,</hi> Fellow of <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel</hi> Coll: who, for that he was born in the ſame Town with me, and had conceived ſome good
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:187792:46"/> opinion of my aptneſſe to learning, enquired di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently concerning me, and hearing of the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of my Fathers purpoſes from the Univerſity, importunately diſſuaded from that <hi>new courſe,</hi> profeſſing to pity the loſſe of ſo <hi>good hopes.</hi> My Brother, partly moved with his words, and partly won by his own eyes, to a great love and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of an <hi>Academical life,</hi> returning home, fell upon his knees to my Father, and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Mr <hi>Gilbies</hi> words, and his own admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place, earneſtly beſought him that he would be pleaſed to alter that ſo prejudicial a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; that he would not ſuffer my hopes to be drowned in a ſhallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Country-chanel,</hi> but that he would revive his firſt purpoſes for <hi>Cambridge;</hi> adding, in the zeal of his love, that if the <hi>charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe</hi> of that courſe were the hinderance, he did there humbly beſeech him, rather to ſell ſome part of that land which himſelf ſhould in courſe of nature inherit, then to abridge me of that happy means to perfect my <hi>Education.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And now I lived in the exſpectation of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>bridge,</hi> whither ere long I happily came, under Mr <hi>Gilbies</hi> tuition, together with my worthy frind Mr <hi>Hugh Cholmly;</hi> who, as we had been partners of one <hi>Leſſon</hi> from our cradles, ſo ſo were we now for many years partners of one <hi>bed.</hi> My <hi>two firſt years</hi> were neceſſarily chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble above the proportion of my Fathers power,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:187792:46"/> whoſe not very large <hi>Ciſtern</hi> was to feed many <hi>pipes</hi> beſides mine; His wearineſſe of expence was wrought upon by the counſel of ſo me unwiſe friends, who perſwaded him to faſten me upon that <hi>School</hi> as Maſter, whereof I was lately a Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Now was I fetch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> home with an heavy heart, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſecond time had mine hopes been nipt in the bloſſom, had not God raiſed me up an unhoped Benefactor, Mr <hi>Edmund Sleigh</hi> of <hi>Darby</hi> (whoſe <hi>pious memorie</hi> I have cauſe ever to love and reverence) out of no other relation to me, ſave that he married my Aunt, pitying my too apparent dejectedneſſe. He voluntarily urged and ſolicited my Father for my <hi>return</hi> to the Univerſity, and offered freely to contribute the one half of my maintenance there, till I ſhould attain to the degree of <hi>Maſter of Arts:</hi> which he no leſſe lovingly perform'd. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition was gladly accepted: thither was I ſent back with joy enough, and ere long choſen <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> of that ſtrict and well ordered <hi>Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. By that time I had ſpent <hi>ſix years</hi> there, now the third year of my Batcherlorſhip ſhould at once make an end of my maintenance, and in reſpect of ſtanding give me a capacity of farther preferment in that houſe, were it not that my <hi>Country</hi> excluded me: for our <hi>Statute</hi> allowed but <hi>one of a ſhire</hi> to be Fellow there, and my <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> being of the ſame Town with me, muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:187792:47"/> neceſſarily hold me out. But the Earl of <hi>Huntingdon</hi> calling off my Tutor from his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, then was I with a cheerful unanimity choſen into <hi>that Societie:</hi> which if it had any equals, I dare ſay had none beyond it, for good order, ſtudious carriage, ſtrict government, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere piety; in which I ſpent ſix or ſeven years more with ſuch contentment, as the reſt of my life hath in vain ſtriven to yeild. Now was I called to publick <hi>Diſputations</hi> often, with no ill ſucceſſe; for neither durſt I appear in any of theſe exerciſes of Scholarſhip, till I had from my knees lookt up to Heaven for a bleſſing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed my actual dependance upon that Divine hand. In this while, two years together, was I choſen to the <hi>Rhetorick Lecture</hi> in the publick School, where I was encouraged with a ſufficient frequence of auditors; but finding that well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded work ſomewhat out of my way, not without a ſecret blame of my ſelf for ſo much excurſion, I fairly gave up that task in the midſt of thoſe poor acclamations to a worthy ſucceſſor, and betook my ſelf to thoſe ſerious ſtudies, which might fit me for that High Calling whereunto I was deſtined. Wherein, after I had beſtowed my ſelf for a time, I took the boldneſſe to enter into <hi>Sacred Orders;</hi> the honour whereof having once attained, I was no niggard of that Talent which my God had entruſted to me, preaching often as
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:187792:47"/> occaſion was offered, both in <hi>Country villages</hi> abroad, and at home in the moſt awful auditory of the <hi>Univerſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And now I did but wait where and how it would pleaſe my God to imploy me. There was at that time a moſt famous <hi>School</hi> erected at <hi>Tiverton</hi> in <hi>Devon,</hi> and endowed with a very large penſion, whoſe goodly fabrick was anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the reported maintenance. To the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this School was I commended by the Maſter of our Houſe Dr <hi>Chaderton,</hi> when being in <hi>London</hi> I received a Letter from the Lady <hi>Drury</hi> of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> tendring the <hi>Rectory</hi> of her <hi>Halſted</hi> then newly void, and very earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring me to accept of it. <hi>Sir,</hi> (quoth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the Doctor) <hi>methinks</hi> God <hi>pulls me by the ſleeve, and tells me it is his will I ſhould rather go to the Eaſt than to the Weſt.</hi> Nay (anſwered he) I ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther think that God would have you go Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for that he hath contrived your engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before the tender of this Letter, which therefore coming too late may receive a fair and eaſie anſwer. To this I beſought him to pardon my diſſent, adding, <hi>That I well knew that Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie was the end whereto I was deſtin'd by my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; which I had ſo conſtantly propoſed to my ſelf, that I never meant other but to paſſe through this Western School to it: but I ſaw that God, who found me ready to go the farther way about, now</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:187792:48"/> 
               <hi>called me the neareſt and directeſt way to that ſacred end.</hi> The good man could no further oppoſe, but only pleaded the diſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t which would hereupon be juſtly taken by the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Popham</hi> (upon whom the care of the School was princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally caſt by the Founder Mr <hi>Blundel)</hi> whom I undertook fully to ſatisfie: which I did with no great difficulty, commending to his Lordſhip in my room, my old friend and Chamber-fellow, Mr <hi>Cholmly,</hi> who finding an anſwerable accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance diſpoſed himſelf to the place. So as we two, who came to the Univerſity, muſt now leave it, at once.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Having then fixed my foot in <hi>Halſted,</hi> I found there a dangerous oppoſite to the ſucceſſe of <hi>my Miniſterie,</hi> a witty and bold Atheiſt, one Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> who, by reaſon of his travels and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of diſcourſe and behaviour, had ſo deeply inſinuated himſelf into my Patron, Sr <hi>Robert Drury,</hi> that there was ſmall hopes, during his entireneſſe, for me to work any good upon that Noble Patron of mine: who, by the ſuggeſtion of this wicked detractor, was ſet off from me before he knew me. Hereupon, I confeſſe, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the obdurateneſſe and hopeleſſe condition of that man, I bent my <hi>prayers</hi> againſt him, beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God dayly, that he would be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, by ſome means o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> othet, that apparent hindrance of my faithful labours: who gave me
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:187792:48"/> an anſwer accordingly: For this malicious man going haſtily to <hi>London,</hi> to exaſperate my Patron againſt me, was then and there ſwept away by the <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> and never returned to do any further miſchief. Now the coaſt was clear before me, and I gained every day of the <hi>good opinion</hi> and favourable reſpects of that Honourable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and my worthy neighbours.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Being now therefore ſetled in that ſweet and civil Country of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> near St <hi>Edmunds-Bury,</hi> my firſt work was to build up <hi>my houſe,</hi> which was extremely ruinous; which done, the uncouth ſolitarineſſe of my life, and the extreme incommodity of that ſingle houſe-keeping, drew my thoughts after two years to condiſcend to the neceſſity of a <hi>married eſtate,</hi> which God no leſſe ſtrangely provided for me. For, walking from the Church on Monday in the Whitſon week, with a grave and reverend Miniſter, Mr <hi>Grandidg,</hi> I ſaw a comely and modeſt <hi>Gentlewoman</hi> ſtanding at the door of that houſe, where we were invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a wedding-dinner, and enquiring of that worthy friend whether he knew her; <hi>Yes,</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth he, <hi>I know her well, and have beſpoken her for your wife.</hi> When I farther demanded an account of that Anſwer, he told me, ſhe was daughter of a Gentleman whom he much reſpected, Mr <hi>George Winniff</hi> of <hi>Bretenham;</hi> that out of an opinion had of the fitneſſe of that Match for me, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:187792:49"/> treated with her Father about it, whom he found very apt to entertain it, adviſing me not to neglect the <hi>opper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unitie:</hi> and not concealing the juſt praiſes of modeſty, piety, good diſpoſition and other virtues that were lodged in that ſeemly preſence, I liſtned to the motion as ſent from <hi>God,</hi> and at laſt upon due proſecution happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, enjoying the comfortable Society of that meet Help for the ſpace of <hi>forty nine years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. I had not paſſed <hi>two years</hi> in this eſtate, when my noble Friend, Sr <hi>Edmund Bacon,</hi> with whom I had much entireneſſe, came to me, and earneſtly ſollicited me for my company in a <hi>Jorny</hi> by him projected to the <hi>Spa</hi> in <hi>Ardenna,</hi> laying before me the ſafety, the eaſineſſe, the pleaſure and the benefit of that ſmall extravagance, if oppertunity were taken of that time, when the Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> paſſed in <hi>Embaſſie</hi> to the Arch-Duke. I ſoon yeelded, as for the reaſons by him urged, ſo eſpecially for the great deſire I had to inform my ſelf <hi>ocularly</hi> of the ſtate and practice of the <hi>Romiſh Church;</hi> the knowledge whereof might be of no ſmall uſe to me in my holy ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Having therefore taken careful order for the ſupply of my Charge, with the aſſent and good allowance of my neareſt Friends, I entred into this ſecret voyage, &amp;c. Returning through <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> we came do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> the Paragon of Cities: where my <hi>curioſitie</hi> to ſee a ſolemn <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:187792:49"/> on S. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>'s day, might have drawn me into <hi>danger</hi> (through my willing unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence) had not the hulk of a tall <hi>Brabanter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind whom I ſtood in the corner of the ſtreet, ſhaded me from notice.</p>
            <p n="9">9. After ſome <hi>year and half,</hi> it pleaſed God inexpectedly to contrive the change of my ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. My means were but ſhort at <hi>Halſted;</hi> yet ſuch, as I oft profeſſed, if my then <hi>Patron</hi> would have added but one ten pounds by year (which I held to be the value of my detained due) I ſhould never have removed. One morning as I lay in my bed, a ſtrong motion was ſuddenly glanced into my thoughts of going to <hi>London.</hi> In <hi>Drurie</hi> lane I was found by a friend in whom I had formerly no great intereſt, one Mr <hi>Gurrey,</hi> Tutor to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex;</hi> he told me how well my <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> were accepted at the <hi>Prince's Court;</hi> and earneſtly adviſed me to ſtep over to <hi>Richmond,</hi> and preach to his Highneſſe. I ſtrongly pleaded my indiſpoſition of body, and my impreparation for any ſuch work, together with my baſhful fears, and utter unfitneſſe for ſuch a preſence; my averſeneſſe doubled his importuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y: in fine, he left me not till he had my engagement <hi>to preach</hi> the Sonday following at <hi>Richmond:</hi> he made way for me to that awful Pulpit, and encouraged me by the favour of his Noble Lord, the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> I preacht through the favour of my God:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:187792:50"/> That Sermon was not ſo well given as taken: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as that ſweet <hi>Prince</hi> ſignified his deſire to hear me again the Tueſday following, which done, that labour gave more contentment than the former; ſo as that gracious Prince, both gave me his hand, and commanded me to his ſervice.</p>
            <p n="10">10. My Patron ſeeing me (upon my return to <hi>London)</hi> lookt after by ſome <hi>great Perſons,</hi> began to wiſh me at home, and told me, <hi>That ſome or other would be ſnatching me up,</hi> I anſwered, <hi>That it was in his power to prevent, would he be pleaſed to make my maintenance, but ſo competent as in right it ſhould be, I ſhould never ſtir from him.</hi> In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ead of condeſcending, it pleaſed him to fall into an expoſtulation of the rate of <hi>competences,</hi> affirming the variableneſſe thereof, according to our own eſtimation, and our either raiſing or moderating the cauſes of our expenſes; I ſhew'd him the inſufficiency of means, that I was forced <hi>to write books to buy books.</hi> Shortly, ſome harſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing anſwer, ſo diſheartned me that I reſolved to embrace the firſt opportunity of <hi>remove.</hi> Now whiles I was taken up with theſe anxious thoughts, a meſſenger (it was Sir <hi>Robert Wingfield</hi> of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampton</hi>'s Son) came to me from the <hi>Lord Denny,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earl of <hi>Norwich,</hi> my after-moſt Honourable Patron, entreating me from his Lordſhip to ſpeak with him. No ſooner came I thither, then
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:187792:50"/> after a glad, and Noble welcom, I was entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Noble earneſt offer of <hi>Waltham.</hi> The conditions were like the mover, free and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful: I received them as from the munificent hands of my <hi>God,</hi> and returned full of the cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acknowledgments of a gratious <hi>Providence</hi> over me. Too late now did my former Noble Patron relent, and offer me thoſe terms which had before faſtned me for ever. I returned home happy in a new maſter, and in a new Patron; betwixt whom I divided my ſelf and my labours, with much comfort and no leſſe acceptation.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In this while, my worthy Kinſman, Mr <hi>Samuel Burton,</hi> Arch-Deacon of <hi>Gloc.</hi> knowing in ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good terms I ſtood at <hi>Court,</hi> and pitying the miſerable condition of his native Church of <hi>Wolverhampton,</hi> was very deſirous to engage me in ſo difficult and noble Service, as the Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that captivated <hi>Church.</hi> Which work ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once firmly ſettled, in a juſt pity of the mean proviſion, if not the deſtitution of ſo many thouſand <hi>ſouls,</hi> and a deſire and care to have them comfortably provided for in the future, I reſigned up my <hi>Prebend</hi> there to a worthy preacher, Mr <hi>Lee,</hi> who ſhould conſtantly reſide, and painfully inſtruct that great and long neglected people: which he hath performed with great mutual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and happy ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Now during <hi>the</hi> 22 <hi>years</hi> which I ſpent at
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:187792:51"/> 
               <hi>Waltham,</hi> thrice was I commanded and employed abroad by his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> in publick ſervice. Firſt in the attendance of the Lord Vicount <hi>Doncaſter,</hi> who was ſent upon a Noble Embaſſie, with a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant retinue into <hi>France.</hi> In this my abſence it pleaſed his Majeſtie gratiouſly to confer upon me the <hi>Deanrie of Worceſter,</hi> which being promiſed me before my departure, was deeply hazarded whiles <hi>I</hi> was out of ſight, by the importunity of ſome great ones. Dr <hi>Field,</hi> the learned and worthy <hi>Doan of Gloceſter,</hi> was, by his potent Friends, put into ſuch aſſurances of it, that <hi>I</hi> heard where he took care for the furniſhing that ample houſe: But, God fetcht it about for me, in that abſence and neſcience of mine, and that reverend and better deſerving Divine was well ſatisfied with greater hopes, and ſoon after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing this mortal eſtate for an immortal and glorious.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Before <hi>I</hi> could go down, through my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual weakneſſe, to take poſſeſſion of that <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> his Majeſty pleaſed to deſign me to his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>dance into <hi>Scotland;</hi> where the great love and reſpect that <hi>I</hi> found, both from the <hi>Miniſters and people,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought me no ſmall envy from ſome of our own. Suggeſtions were made to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of my pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſible deme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nour and doctrine to that already prejudicate people: for which his Majeſty, after a gracious acknowledgment of my
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:187792:51"/> good ſervice there done, called me upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to a favorable and mild <hi>account;</hi> not more freely profeſſing what informations had been given againſt me, then his own full ſatisfaction with my ſincere and juſt anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as whoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wiſdom well ſaw, that ſuch <hi>winning carriage</hi> of mine could be no hinderance to his great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. At the ſame time his Majeſty having ſecret notice, that a <hi>Letter</hi> was coming to me from Mr <hi>W. Struther,</hi> a Reverend and Learned Divine of <hi>Edenborough</hi> concerning <hi>the five points</hi> then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and urged to the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was pleaſed to impoſe upon me an earneſt charge to give him a full <hi>Anſwer</hi> to thoſe modeſt Doubts, and at large to declare my Judgment concerning thoſe required <hi>Obſervations.</hi> Which I ſpedily performed with ſo great approbation of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, that it pleaſed him to command a <hi>tranſcript</hi> thereof, as I was informed, publickly read in their moſt famous Univerſity. The effe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, his Majeſtie vouchſafed to ſignifie afterwards unto ſome of my beſt friends, with allowance beyond my hopes.</p>
            <p n="14">14. It was not long after, that his Majeſtie finding the exigence of the Netherlandiſh Churches to require it, both adviſed them to <hi>a Synodical Deciſion,</hi> and by his incomparable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom promoted the work. My un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthineſſe was named for one of the <hi>Aſſistants</hi> of that Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:187792:52"/> Grave and Reverent Meeting; where I fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not of my beſt ſervice of that woful diſtracted Church. By that time I had ſtaid two months there, the unquietneſſe of the nights, in thoſe Garriſon Towns, working upon the tender diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of my body, brought me to ſuch weakneſs, through want of reſt, that it began to diſable me from attending the Synod. Yet it pleaſed God, the very night before I was to preach the <hi>Latin Sermon</hi> to the Synod, to beſtow upon me ſuch a comfortable refreſhing of ſufficient ſleep, as whereby my ſpirits were revived, and I was enabled with much vivacity to perform that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. But when, notwithſtanding all means, my weakneſſe encreaſed, it pleaſed his gracious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie to call me off, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="15">15. After not many years ſettling at home, it grieved my Soul, to ſee <hi>our own Church</hi> ſicken of the ſame diſeaſe, which we had endeavoured to cure in our Neighbours. Sides were taken, and Pulpits every where rang of theſe <hi>opinions.</hi> Now, as one that deſired to do all good offices to our dear and common <hi>Mother,</hi> I ſet my thoughts on work, how ſo dangerous a quarrel might be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily compoſed, and wrote a little projeſt of <hi>Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> gathering out of Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi> on the one ſide, and out of our <hi>Engliſh Divines</hi> at <hi>Dort</hi> on the other, ſuch common propoſitions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe five buſie Articles, as wherein both of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:187792:52"/> them are fully agreed. Theſe <hi>reconciliatory papers</hi> were preſented to his Majeſtie, together with an humble motion of a peaceſible <hi>ſilence</hi> to be enjoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to both parts, in thoſe other collateral &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Diſputations. Theſe fell under the eyes of ſome grave <hi>Divines</hi> of both parts, who p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oferd their hands to a ready <hi>ſubſcription:</hi> ſo as much peace promiſed to reſult out of that weak and poor enterprize, had not the confuſed noiſe of the miſconſtructions of thoſe, who never ſaw the work (crying it down for the very name ſake) meeting with the royal edict of a general <hi>Inhiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> buried it in a ſecure ſilence. I was ſcorched a little with this flame, which I de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ired to quench; yet this could not ſtay my hand from thru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing it ſelf into a hotter fire.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Some inſolent <hi>Romaniſts</hi> preſſed nothing ſo much, as a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the profeſſions of our Religion; to be deduced from the Primitive times, and with the peremtory challenge of the impoſſibility of this pedigree dazled the eyes of the ſimple. Whiles ſome of our learned men, undertaking to ſatisfie ſo needleſſe and unjuſt a demand, gave, as I conceive, great advantage to the Adverſary; in a juſt indignation, to ſee us thus wrongd by miſtareing the Queſtion betwixt us, as if we, yeelding our ſelves of <hi>another Church,</hi> originally and fundamentally different, ſhould make good our own E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection upon the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:187792:53"/> Ruines, yea and Nullity of others; and well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the infinite and great inconveniences, that muſt needs follow upon this defence; <hi>I</hi> adventured to ſet my pen on work, (deſiring to rectifie the opinions of thoſe men, whom an <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant zeal</hi> had tranſported, to the prejudice of our holy cauſe,) laying forth the damnable <hi>corruptions</hi> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oman <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch, yet making our Game at the <hi>outward viſibilitie</hi> thereof, and by this means putting them to the probation of thoſe newly obtruded corruptions, which are truly guilty of the breach betwixt us. The drift whereof being not well conceived by ſome ſpirits, that were <hi>not ſo wiſe as fervent, I</hi> was ſuddenly expoſed to the raſh cenſures of many well affected and zealous Proteſtants; as if a Remiſſion to my wonted zeal to the truth, attributed too much to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church,</hi> and ſtrengthned the Adverſaries hands, and weakned our own. This envy I was fain to take off by my ſpeedy <hi>Apologetical Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement,</hi> and after that by my <hi>Reconcilor,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ded with the unanimous <hi>Letters</hi> of ſuch Reverend, Learned, ſound Divines, both Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Doctors, as whoſe undoubtable Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity was able to bear down calumny it ſelf. Which done <hi>I</hi> did, by a ſeaſonable <hi>Moderation,</hi> provide for the peace of the Church, in ſilencing both my <hi>Defendants</hi> and <hi>Challengers,</hi> in this unkind and ill-raiſed quarrel.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:187792:53"/> 17. Immediatly before the publiſhing of this <hi>Tractate</hi> (which did not a little aggravate the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and ſuſpicion) <hi>I</hi> was by his Majeſty raiſed to be <hi>Biſhop of Exeter,</hi> having formerly with humble deprecation, refuſed the See of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly proferd to me. I entred upon that place, not without much prejudice and ſuſpicion on ſome hands. For ſome, that ſate at the <hi>Stern</hi> of the Church, had me in great jealouſie for too much favour of <hi>Puritaniſus. I</hi> ſoon had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, who were ſet over me for <hi>Eſpials:</hi> my waies were curiouſly obſerved and ſcanned. However <hi>I</hi> took the reſolution to follow thoſe courſes, which might moſt conduce to the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>happineſſe</hi> of my ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and weighty charge. Finding therefore ſome factious ſpirits very buſie in that <hi>Dioceſſe, I</hi> uſed all fair and gentle means to win them to good order; and therein ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily prevailed, that (ſaving two of that numerous Clergy, who continuing in their refracto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ineſſe fled away from cenſure) they were all pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fectly <hi>reclaimed:</hi> ſo as <hi>I</hi> had not one Miniſter profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly oppoſite to the antiently received <hi>Orders</hi> (for <hi>I</hi> was never guilty of urging any ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of the Church in that large Dio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs.</p>
            <p n="18">18. In the laſt year of preſiding the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, after the <hi>Synodical Oath</hi> was ſet on foot (which yet I did never tender to any one Miniſter of my Dioceſs) by the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itation of ſome bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:187792:54"/> interlopers of the neighbour County, ſome of them began to enter into an unkind conteſtation with me, about the <hi>election of Clerks</hi> for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; whom they ſecre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, without ever acquainting me with their deſire or purpoſe (as driving to <hi>that end</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich we ſee now accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed) would needs nominate and ſet up in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition to thoſe, whom <hi>I</hi> had (after the uſual form) recommended to them. That they had a right to <hi>free voices</hi> in that choice, <hi>I</hi> deny not: only <hi>I</hi> had reaſon to take it unkindly, that they would work underhand without me and <hi>againſt me.</hi> It came to the poll: thoſe of my nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion carried it: the Parliament begun: after ſome <hi>hard tugging</hi> there; returning ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon a receſſe, <hi>I</hi> was met by the way and chearfully welcomed by ſome hundreds.</p>
            <p n="19">19. In no worſe terms, <hi>I</hi> left that my once dear Dioceſe: when returning to <hi>Weſtminster, I</hi> was ſoon called by his Majeſtie (who was then in the North) to a remove to <hi>Norwich.</hi> But how <hi>I</hi> took the <hi>Tower</hi> in my way, and how <hi>I</hi> have been dealt with ſince my repair hither, <hi>I</hi> could be laviſh in the ſad report, ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring <hi>my good God</hi> to enlarge my heart in thankfulneſſe to him, for the ſenſible expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience <hi>I</hi> have had of his <hi>Fatherly Hand</hi> over me, in the deepeſt of all my Afflctions, and to ſtrengthen me, for whatſoever other <hi>tryals</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:187792:54"/> he ſhall be pleaſed to call me unto: That being found <hi>faithful unto the death, I</hi> may obtain that <hi>Crown of life,</hi> which he hath ordained for all thoſe that overcome.</p>
            <closer>See Biſhop Hall's Hard Meaſure.</closer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="biography">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:187792:55"/>
            <head>VI. Sr <hi>THOMAS MORE,</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Life, Written by</hi> J. H. D. Timotheo Norwood e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Int. Temp.</head>
            <figure>
               <head>UERA EFFIGIES THOMAE MORI QVONDAM TOTIUS ANGLIAE CANCELLARII DIGNISSIMI ETc.</head>
            </figure>
            <p n="2">2. The Arch-biſhop for his advance in learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſent him to <hi>Cant:</hi> Coll. (now <hi>Chriſt-Church)</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Thence he removed to <hi>New Inn,</hi> an Inne of Chancery, to ſtudy the Law: then to <hi>Lincolns Inn,</hi> where he was made Barriſter. And then he for ſome time read upon S. <hi>Auſtins de Civ. Dei,</hi> in S. <hi>Laurence Church,</hi> where his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures were frequented by <hi>Grocin</hi> and other learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men: then, for three years was he eader in <hi>Furnivals Inn:</hi> after which, for about four years, he gave himſelf to ſtudy and devotion in the <hi>Charter-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He was (firſt) maried to Mr <hi>Coles</hi> daughter of New-hall in <hi>Eſsex,</hi> and lived with her in <hi>Bucklers-burie</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> where he had by her one Son and three Daughters, whom he brought up in <hi>virtue and learning,</hi> often exhorting them <hi>to take that for their meat, and play but for their ſauce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In the later end of K. <hi>Henry</hi> 7. he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kings diſpleaſure, for oppoſing the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition propoſed in Parliament toward the match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> Which he argued againſt ſtrongly, that one of the Privy Chamber told the King, <hi>A beardleſſe Boy had</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:187792:57"/> 
               <hi>fruſtrated all his expectations.</hi> To avoid danger he determined to have gone over Sea, but the Kings death happening ſoon after acquitted him of his fear.</p>
            <p n="4">4. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is he made <hi>under-Sheriff</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> by which office, and his learning together, he gained (as himſelf ſaid) without grudge of conſcience 400l <hi>per an.</hi> for he was of Counſel in moſt cauſes, choo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ever the juſteſt ſide, and for the moſt part victorious. Twice was he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed abroad by the Kings con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt in ſome great Cauſes of the <hi>Merchants.</hi> Being called by Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſie</hi> to the Kings ſervice, he excuſed himſelf at firſt, but at laſt (his fame and merit encreaſing) the King would take no denial. Thus is he made <hi>Maſter of the requeſts:</hi> within a month Knighted, and one of the <hi>Privy Council;</hi> continuing in his Majeſties favour and truſty ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice twenty years and above. In good part of which time, the King was ſo pleaſed with his converſe, and taken with the variety of his learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pleaſant diſcourſe, that Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> ſcarce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ained time (till he abated of his former mirth) once in a month to go home to his wife and children. The King, upon the death of <hi>Weſton,</hi> without asking, freely advanced him to be <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of the Exchequer,</hi> and in the 14 year of his Majeſties raign was he choſen <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:187792:57"/> 5. At this Parliament he croſſed the <hi>Cardinal</hi> and incurred his diſpleaſure, ſo that in revenge he counſelled the King to ſend Sr <hi>Thomas Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> commending his wiſdom, learning and fitneſſe for that employment. But, Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> having declared to his Majeſtie how unfit a journy it was for him to undertake, the nature of the Country and his complexion ſo diſagreeing, <hi>that if he were ſent thither, he ſhould be ſent to his grave:</hi> nevertheleſſe being ready with the peril of his life to fulfil his Majeſties pleaſure; the King graciouſly ſaid. <hi>It is not our meaning Mr More to do you hurt, but to do you good we would be glad: we therefore will think of ſome other, and employ your ſervice otherwiſe.</hi> And ſuch entire favour did the King bear him, that upon the death of <hi>Wingfield</hi> he preferred him to be <hi>Chancellor</hi> of the Dutchy of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. K. <hi>Henrie</hi> took ſo great pleaſure in Sr <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>'s company, that he would ſuddenly come to his houſe at <hi>Clelſey</hi> to be merry with him; and once, after dinner walking in the Garden, about an hour embraced his neck. After, when his ſon <hi>Roper</hi> rejoiced at it: <hi>I have no cauſe to be proud of it</hi> (quoth Sr <hi>Thomas) for if my head would win him a Caſtle in France, it would not fail to go off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Sr <hi>Thomas More;</hi> though in great honour and favour with his Prince, was not therefore
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:187792:58"/> puft up with pride, diſdain or arrogancy, but was of ſuch a mild behaviour and excellent temper, that his Son in Law witneſſeth; <hi>For ſixteen years time and more that he dwelt in his houſe, and was converſant with him, he could never perceive him ſo much as once in a paſſion.</hi> If he child any for a fault, it was with exceeding love and compaſſion: if he fortuned to argue with any learned man (as he was viſited by many) when he perceived his adverſarie to be in a ſtreit, he would by ſome witty invention break off and fall into ſome other matter.</p>
            <p n="8">8. When Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> was employed by the King in <hi>Flanders,</hi> an arrogant fellow had ſet up a <hi>Theſis,</hi> that he would anſwer any queſtion could be propounded to him in what Art ſoever. Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> made this queſtion to be put up for him to anſwer, <hi>An Averia capta in Withernamia ſint irreplegebilia,</hi> adding, that there was one of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbaſſadors retinue, that would diſpute with him thereof. This Thraſo, not ſo much as underſtanding thoſe terms of our Common Law, became ridiculous to all the town for his brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</p>
            <p n="9">9. As he walked by the Thames ſide near <hi>Chelſey,</hi> in diſcourſe, he ſaid: <hi>Now, would to our Lord, upon condition that three things were well eſtabliſhed in Chriſtendom, I were put into a ſack, and here preſently caſt into the Thames.</hi> Being
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:187792:58"/> asked, what thoſe three things were, he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: 1. <hi>That where moſt part of Chriiſtian Princes be now at mortal war, they were at an univerſal peace.</hi> 2. <hi>That where the Church of Chriſt is at this time ſore afflicted with many errors and hereſies, it were ſettled in a perfect uniformitie of Religion.</hi> 3. <hi>That whereas the Kings marriage is now brought in queſtion, it were to the glorie of God and quietneſs of all parties well concluded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. When he obſerved any of his to ſpend much time in dreſſing themſelves, to be fine in their Apparel, he would tell them: <hi>That if God gave them not hell, he ſhould do them much wrong; for they took more pains to pleaſe the world and the Divel, than many even virtuous men did to clenſe their ſouls and pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. To his wife and children, when at any time they were troubled, he would ſay: <hi>We may not look at our pleaſure to go to heaven in fether-beds that is not the way. For our Lord himſelf went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through pain, and many tribulations: and the ſervant may not look to be in better condition than the maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. The King ſent the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> and Sr <hi>Thomas More</hi> Embaſſadors to <hi>Cambray</hi> (a place, then, neither <hi>Imperial</hi> nor <hi>French)</hi> to treat of a peace between the Emperor and the <hi>French</hi> King and Him. In the concluſion, Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> ſo worthily behaved himſelf (procuring in the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:187792:59"/> league far more advantages unto this Kingdom, than at that time by the King or his Council was thought poſſible) that for his good ſervice in that employment, the King made him <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> and cauſed the Dukes of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> to bring him through Weſtmin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er-hall to his place in the Chancery. Where the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> in audience of all the people there aſſembled, ſhewed that he was from the King himſelf ſtreit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged by commiſſion, there openly in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them all, to make Declaration how much all <hi>England</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as heholding to Sr <hi>Tho. More</hi> for his <hi>good ſervice,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd how worthy he was of the higheſt preferment in the Kingdom, and how dearly his Grace loved and truſted him.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Now upon Sr <hi>Tho: More</hi>'s entrance into this honorable <hi>Office,</hi> every one might perceive a very ſtrange alteration. For, whereas the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chancellor <hi>Wolſey</hi> would ſcarce look or ſpeak to any; into whoſe only preſence none could be admitted unleſſe his fingers were <hi>tipt</hi> with gold: on the contrary, this Chancellor, the poorer and meaner the Suppliant was, the more affably he would ſpeak unto him, the more atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively he would hearken to his cauſe, and with ſpeedy tryal diſpatch him. For which purpoſe he uſed commonly every afternoon to ſit in his <hi>Hall,</hi> that if any Perſon watſoever had any ſute unto him, they might the more boldly come into
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:187792:59"/> his preſence, and open their complaints before him. To ſhew his integrity, he profeſſed: <hi>If the parties will at my hands call for juſtice, though my Father, whom I dearly love, ſtood on the one ſide, and the Divel, whom I extremely hate, ſtood on the other, his cauſe being good, the Devil ſhould have right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The <hi>Biſhops</hi> (conſidering his learned works in defence of religion, and knowing that (for all his Princes favour) he was no rich man, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in yearly revenues, as his worthineſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) agreed together in <hi>Convocation,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded upon a ſum of <hi>four or five thouſand pounds</hi> to recompence him for his pains. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſtal</hi> and ſome other Biſhops repaired to him, and declared, That albeit they could not according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts ſo worthily requite him as they gladly would, but muſt refer that only to the <hi>goodneſs of God;</hi> yet for a ſmall part of recompence, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his eſtate ſo unequal to his worthineſſe, in the name of their whole Convocation, they preſented to him that ſum, which they deſired him to accept of. To whom he anſwered: <hi>That like as it was no ſmall comfort to him, that ſo wiſe and learned men ſo well accepted o his doings, for which he never intended to receive reward but at the hands of God only, to whom alone was the thanks thereof chiefly to be aſcribed; ſo alſo he moſt humbly thanked the Honors for their bountiful conſideration;</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:187792:60"/> But, for all their importunity, they could not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten it upon him, nor would he ſuffer them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it upon his wife and children.</p>
            <p n="15">15. He behaved himſelf in his office of the Chancellorſhip (for the ſpace of two years and a half) ſo <hi>wiſely</hi> that none could mend his doings, ſo <hi>uprightly</hi> that none could take exception againſt him, ſo <hi>dextrouſly</hi> that (tis to be ſuppoſed) never any man before or ſince did that which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did. For he had taken ſuch order for the diſpatching of all mens cauſes, that on a time ſitting as Judge there, and having finiſhed one cauſe, calling for the next to be heard, anſwer was made, <hi>That there was not one cauſe more depending.</hi> This he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be ſet down upon <hi>Record.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. After he had obtained of the King a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge</hi> from his office, he fell into his Majeſties diſpleaſure about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Marriage.</hi> And then was he accuſed for receiving a <hi>bribe</hi> from one <hi>Vaughans</hi> wife. The matter being laid to his charge before the Council, he confeſſed, that a gilt Cup being (long after a certain Decree) brought him for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w years gift, and preſſed on him, in courteſie <hi>he received it.</hi> Whereupon his Adverſary with much joy ſaid, <hi>Lo, my Lords, did I not tell y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, that you ſhould find the matter true?</hi> Sr <hi>Thomas</hi> deſiring their Lordſhips to hear him out, <hi>It is true,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I did, being much urged, receive that Cup, but immediately cauſed my Butler to fill it with wine,</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:187792:60"/> 
               <hi>drank to the Gentle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oman, and freelie gave it to her again to be preſented to her husband, as a New years gift for him.</hi> This being teſtified preſently upon oath of the party her ſelf and others, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was delivered of a Mouſe.</p>
            <p n="17">17. After the King's indignation againſt Sir <hi>Thomas More,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Norfolk</hi> and He chanced to fall in diſcourſe, and amongſt other talk, the Duke ſaid unto him, <hi>By the Maſſe, Mr</hi> More, <hi>it is perillous ſtriving with Princes, and therefore I would wiſh you ſomewhat to incline to the Kings pleaſure. For,</hi> Indignatio Principis mors eſt. <hi>Is that all, my Lord,</hi> ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas, Then in good faith is there no more difference betwixt your Grace and me, but that I ſhall dye to day and you to morrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. When he was ſent unto the Tower (for not ſwearing to the Oath of Supre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acy and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion) at his entrance there, the Porter deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him his upper garment. <hi>Mr Porter,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>here it is:</hi> and took off his Cap and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve it him: <hi>I am ſorrie it is no better for thee.</hi> No Sir, ſaid the Porter, <hi>I muſt have your Gown,</hi> which he gave him.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Lieutenant coming into his chamber to viſit him, profeſſed himſelf obliged by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer favours to ente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in him nobly: which ſince he could not do for fear of the Kings diſpleaſure, he prayed him to accept of his good will, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:187792:61"/> ſuch poor fare as he had: <hi>Maſter Lieutenant</hi> (quoth Sir <hi>Thomas) I believe you are my frind, I thank you for your good will, and I aſſure you I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not miſlike my cheer: but whenſoever I do, then thruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me out of your doors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, he had begun a Divine Treatiſe <hi>of the Paſſion of Chriſt,</hi> and when he came to theſe words of the Goſpel, <hi>(And the) laid hands on him and held him)</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook from him all his Books, Ink, and Paper, ſo that he could go on no further. Afterwards, he applyed himſelf holly to <hi>Meditation,</hi> keeping his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber windows faſt ſhut and very dark; the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof the Lieutenant asking; <hi>It is time</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when all the wares are gone to ſhut up ſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. After he had received the ſentence of death, he ſaid to the Judges: <hi>My Lords, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read that Paul conſented to the death of Stephen, and yet be they now both Saints in Heaven, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue there friends for ever; ſo I verily truſt, and ſhall therefore right heartily pray, that though your L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dſhips have been now Judges on earth to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, we may yet hereafter all meet together in Heaven merrily to our everlaſting ſalvation. And ſo I pray God preſerve my Soveraign Lord the King, and ſend him faithful Councellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>*See the reſt, if you pleaſe, in this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or in <hi>Stapleton</hi>'s Latin book, <hi>Detribus Thomis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:61"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:62"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Henry Wotton K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="biography">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:187792:62"/>
            <head>VII. Sr <hi>HENRY WOTTON.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of his Life written by Mr</hi> Iz: Walton. D. Roberto Jones, Rect. de Leckhampton.</head>
            <p n="1">1. SIR <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> was born An. 1568. in <hi>Bocton-Hall,</hi> in the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh of <hi>Bocto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Malherb,</hi> in the fruitful Country of <hi>Kent:</hi> both <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> ſeated within a fair Park of the <hi>Wottons,</hi> on the brow of ſuch a hill as gives the advantage of a large proſpect, and of equal pleaſure to all behol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers. But they are not rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble for any thing ſo much, as for that the memorable <hi>Familie</hi> of the <hi>Wottons</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve ſo long inh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bited the one, and now lie bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied in the other, as appears by their m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny <hi>Monuments</hi> in that Church; the <hi>Wottons</hi> being a Family, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th divers Perſons eminent for <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Valour,</hi> whoſe Heroick Acts and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:187792:63"/> Noble Employments, both in <hi>England</hi> and in Forein parts, have adorned themſelves and this Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Thomas Wotton</hi> (the <hi>Father</hi> of our <hi>Henrie)</hi> was a <hi>Gent.</hi> excellently educated and ſtudious in all the liberal <hi>Arts:</hi> who, although he had many invitations from Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to change his <hi>Countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> recreations and retirement for a <hi>Court life,</hi> offering him a <hi>Knighthood</hi> (ſhe was then with him at his <hi>Bocton-hall)</hi> and to be but as an earneſt of ſome more honorable and more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table imployment under her, yet he humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth both; <hi>being a man of great modeſtie, of a most plain and ſingle heart, of an antient freedom and integritie of mind:</hi> A commendation, which Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> took occaſion often to remember with great gladneſs, and thankfully to boaſt himſelf <hi>the Son of ſuch a Father:</hi> from whom indeed he deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that noble <hi>Ingenuitie</hi> that was alwaies practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by himſelf, and which he ever commended and cheriſhed in others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of this Family was <hi>Nicholas Wotton Doctor of Law,</hi> and ſometime <hi>Dean of Canterburie:</hi> a man whom God did not only bleſſe with a long life, but with great abilitiès of mind, and an inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to employ them in the ſervice of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; as is reſtified by his ſeveral imployments, having been ſent <hi>nine times Embaſſador</hi> unto forein Princes, a Privy Councellor to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Henrie</hi> 8
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:187792:63"/> 
               <hi>Edward</hi> 6. <hi>Q. Marie</hi> and <hi>Q. Elizabeth:</hi> who imployed him three ſeveral times for ſetling of peace between <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> who alſo offered him the <hi>Archbiſhoprick of Cant.</hi> but he refuſed it, and dyed not rich, though he had lived in the time of diſſolution of Abbies. <hi>He dyed</hi> (ſaith learned <hi>Camden) full of commendation for Wiſdom and Pietie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Father of Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> after the death of his firſt wife reſolved, if he ſhould marry again, to avoid three ſorts of perſons; namely, <hi>thoſe that had children, or had law ſuits, or were of his kinred.</hi> And yet, following his own Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, he met in Weſtminſter-hall with one Mrs <hi>Morton</hi> widow, (daughter to Sir <hi>William Finch</hi> of <hi>Kent)</hi> who was alſo ingaged in ſeveral ſuits in Law: and obſerving her <hi>Comportment</hi> at the time of hearing one of her Cauſes before the Judges, he could not but at the ſame time both compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate her <hi>condition,</hi> and ſo affect her <hi>perſon,</hi> that although there was in her a concurrence of all thoſe accidents againſt which he had reſolved, yet he ſollicited her for a wife and obtained her. By her he had our <hi>Henrie,</hi> his youngeſt ſon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His <hi>Mother</hi> was Tutoreſſe to him during his childhood: for hich care and pains he paid her every day with ſuch viſible ſigns of future perfection in learning, as turned her imployment into a <hi>pleaſing trouble.</hi> After, his <hi>Father</hi> took
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:187792:64"/> him into his particular care, and diſpoſed of him to a <hi>Tutor</hi> in his own houſe: and when time and diligent inſtruction had fitted him (which was very early) he was ſent to <hi>Winch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter School,</hi> a place of ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ict Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipline and Order, that ſo he might in his youth be mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded into a method of <hi>living by rule.</hi> And that he might be confirmed in this <hi>Regularitie,</hi> he was at a fit age removed from that School to <hi>New Coll:</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. There he continued till about the 18th year of his age, and was then tranſplanted into <hi>Queens</hi> Coll. where within that year he wrote a <hi>Play</hi> for their private uſe, <hi>the Tragedie of Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credo,</hi> ſo ell, that the graveſt of that Society declared, he had in a ſlight exerciſe given an early and a ſolid te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imony of future abilities. About the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of his age, he proceeded <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> and at that time read in Latin three Lectures <hi>De oculo:</hi> wherein, having deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the form, motion, curious compoſure of the <hi>eye,</hi> &amp;c. in the concluſion he took a fair occaſion to beautifie his diſcourſe with a commendation of the bleſſing and benefit of ſeeing; ſo exactly and Rhetorically, as, among other admirers, cauſed that learned <hi>Italian Albericus Gentilis</hi> (then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of the Civil Law in <hi>Oxford)</hi> to call him, <hi>Henrice mi ocelle;</hi> which dear expreſſion of his was uſed by many other perſons of note, during his ſtay in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:187792:64"/> 7. After his <hi>Optick Lecture,</hi> he was taken into ſuch a boſom friendſhip with <hi>Gentilis,</hi> that if it had been poſſible, he would have breathed all his excellent knowledge both of the <hi>Mathematicks and Law</hi> into the breaſt of his <hi>dear Henrie</hi> (for ſo he uſed to call him) and though he was not able to do that, yet there was in Sir <hi>Harrie</hi> ſuch a propenſity and connaturalneſſe to the <hi>Italian lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> and thoſe ſtudies whereof <hi>Gentilis</hi> was a great Maſter, that this friendſhip between them did dayly increaſe and proved dayly advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> for the improvement of him in ſeveral Sciences. Among his other friends in <hi>Oxford,</hi> I muſt not omit the mention of a love there begun between him and Dr <hi>Donne</hi> (whom, he of this nation, who pretends to learning or ingenuity, and is ignorant of, deſerves not to kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) This <hi>friendſhip</hi> was generouſly elemented, and as it was begun in their <hi>Youth</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and there maintained by correſpondent incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and ſtudies, ſo it laſted till <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> forced a ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The year after Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> proceeded <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Arts;</hi> his Father (whom he did never mention without this or ſome like reverential expreſſion, <hi>That good man my Father)</hi> changed this for a better life, leaving to Sr <hi>Henry,</hi> as to his other younger ſons, a rent charge of an <hi>hundred Marks</hi> a year to be paid for ever out of one of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:187792:65"/> his Mannors of a much greater value. About two years after, being about t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o and twenty, and having to his great <hi>Wit</hi> added the ballaſt of <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> he laid aſide his Books, and betook himſelf to <hi>travel</hi> and a more general converſation with Mankind: imploying the remaining part of his youth to purchaſe the rich treaſure of <hi>forein know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg.</hi> Of which, both for the ſecrets of nature, the diſpoſitions of many Nations, their ſeveral Laws and Languages, he became the poſſeſſor in a very large meaſure.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In his <hi>Travels</hi> (which was almoſt <hi>nine years</hi> before his return into <hi>England)</hi> he ſtayed but <hi>one</hi> year in <hi>France,</hi> and moſt of that in <hi>Geneva:</hi> where he became acquainted with <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> (then very aged) and with <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> that moſt learned man. <hi>Three</hi> of the remaining eight years were ſpent in <hi>Germanie,</hi> the other <hi>five</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> the ſtage on which God appointed he ſhould act a great part of his life) where both in <hi>Rome, Venice,</hi> and <hi>Florence,</hi> he became acquainted with the moſt eminent men for learning and all manner of <hi>Arts,</hi> as <hi>Picture, Sculpture, Chymiſtrie, Architecture,</hi> and divers other manual Arts, even Arts of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour nature: of all which he was a moſt dear <hi>lover,</hi> and a moſt excellent <hi>Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. He returned out of <hi>Italy</hi> into <hi>England</hi> about the 30th year of his Age, being then noted by many, both for his perſon and comportment.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:187792:65"/> For indeed he was of <hi>a choice ſhape,</hi> tall of <hi>ſtature,</hi> and of a moſt pleaſant <hi>behaviour:</hi> which was ſo mixed with ſweet <hi>diſcourſe</hi> and civilities, as gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him much love from all perſons with whom he entred into an acquaintance. And whereas he was noted in his youth to have a ſharp wit and apt to jeſt; That, by time, travel and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was ſo poliſhed and made uſeful, that his <hi>companie</hi> ſeemed to be one of the <hi>delights of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi> In ſo much as <hi>Robert</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> (then one of the darlings of fortune) invited him firſt into a friendſhip, and after a knowledge of his great Abilities, to be one of his <hi>Secretaries.</hi> After the Earls <hi>Apprehenſion,</hi> he paſſed into <hi>France</hi> and thence into <hi>Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> After ſome ſtay in <hi>France,</hi> (where he met with his old friend <hi>Vietta,</hi> then Secretary to the great Duke) he went the fourth time to viſit <hi>Rome,</hi> and injoyed the company of his friends (notwithſtanding his Religion) in the <hi>Engliſh Colledge,</hi> and ſatisfied himſelf concerning ſome <hi>curioſities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. After his return to <hi>Florence,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intercepted certain Letters that diſcove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed a deſign to take away the life of the then King of <hi>Scots,</hi> ſent Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> to impart it to the King, under the name of <hi>Octovio Paldi</hi> an <hi>Italian.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deliverd his Letters and Meſſage, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately told the King that he was indeed in <hi>Ergliſh-man,</hi> he abode there three months with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:187792:66"/> much pleaſure to his Majeſtie, and ſo returned to <hi>Florence</hi> with a fair account of his imployment. Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſome few months after depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and King <hi>James</hi> was proclaimed. When he was come into <hi>England,</hi> he commanded the Lord <hi>Wotton</hi> to fend for his Brother <hi>Henrie.</hi> Being brought to the King, he took him in his arms and bade him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elcome by the name of <hi>Octovio Baldi,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He was the moſt honeſt, and therefore the beſt diſſembler that ever he met with;</hi> adding, <hi>Since I know you neither want learning, travel nor experience, and that I have had ſo real a teſtimonie of your faithfulneſs and abilities to manage an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, I ſhall make uſe of you in that kind here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> And indeed the King did ſo, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of thoſe 22 years of his raign: but before he diſmiſt <hi>Octavio Baldi</hi> from his preſent attendance upon him, he reſto ed him to his old name of <hi>Henrie Wotton,</hi> by which he then <hi>Knighted</hi> him.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Not long after this, the <hi>King</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, according to his Motto, <hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friendſhip with his neighbour Kingdoms of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> and alſo for divers weighty reaſons to enter into an alliance with the <hi>State of Ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to that end to ſend <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> to theſe ſeveral places; did propoſe the choice of theſe employments to Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton.</hi> Who conſidering the ſmalneſſe of his own <hi>eſtate</hi> (which he never took care to augment) and knowing the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:187792:66"/> 
               <hi>Courts</hi> of great Princes to be ſumptuous and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily expenſive, inclined moſt to that of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> as being a place of more retirement and beſt ſuiting with his <hi>Genius,</hi> who did ever love to joyn with buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe <hi>ſtud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> and a tryal of natural <hi>experience;</hi> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which, fruitful <hi>Italy, that darling of nature, and cheriſher of all arts,</hi> is ſo juſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in all parts of the Chriſtian World. Having therefore reſolved upon <hi>Venice,</hi> and a large allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e being appointed by the King for his voyage thither, and a ſettled maintenance during his ſtay there, he left <hi>England,</hi> nobly accompanied through <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Venice</hi> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entlemen of the beſt Families and Breeding that this Nation afforded. Sir <hi>Albertus Morton</hi> his Nephew went his <hi>Secretarie,</hi> and <hi>William Bedel,</hi> a man of choice learning and ſanctified wiſdom, his <hi>Chaplain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>An.</hi> 1605. Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi> was received by the State of <hi>Venice</hi> with much honour and gladneſſe, both for that he delivered his Embaſſage moſt elegantly in the <hi>Italian Language,</hi> and came alſo in ſuch a juncture of time, as his Maſters friendſhip ſeemed uſeful for that Republick. In the contention with the <hi>Pope</hi> (which laſted ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years) the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſtill acquainted K. <hi>James</hi> with their proceedings, by the help of Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton,</hi> Mr <hi>Bedel,</hi> and <hi>Padre Paulo,</hi> whom the <hi>Venetians</hi> did then call to be one of their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultors of State,</hi> and with his pen to defend their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:187792:67"/> cauſe. Which was by him ſo performed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> ſaw plainly, he had weakned his power by exceeding it, and offered the <hi>Venetians Abſolution</hi> upon very eaſie terms; which the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſtill ſlighting, did at laſt obtain by that which was ſcarce ſo much as a ſhew of acknowledging it. Theſe Conteſts were the occaſion of <hi>Padre Paulo</hi> his knowledge and intereſt with K. <hi>James:</hi> for whoſe ſake principally Father <hi>Paulo</hi> compiled that eminent <hi>Hiſtorie of the Council of Trent.</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich Hiſtory was, as faſt as it was written, ſent in ſeveral ſheets in Letters by Sir <hi>H. Wotton,</hi> Mr <hi>Bedel</hi> and others unto K. <hi>James,</hi> and the then B. of <hi>Cant:</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and there firſt made publick both in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngliſh and in the Univerſal Language.</p>
            <p n="14">14. For eight years after Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi>'s going into <hi>Italie,</hi> he ſtood fair, and highly valued but at laſt became much clouded by this accident Being merry with his friends at <hi>Auguſta</hi> (men of. the beſt note for learning and ingenuouſneſs, the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> of that Nation) he was requeſted by <hi>Chriſtopher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lecamore</hi> to write ſome Sentence in his <hi>Albo</hi> (a book of white paper, which for that purpoſe many of the <hi>German</hi> Gentry uſually carry about them) and conſenting to the motion, took an occaſion from ſome accidental diſcourſe of the preſent company, to write a pleaſant definition of an Embaſſador in theſe very words: <hi>Legatus eſt Vir bonus peregrè miſsus ad mentiendum Reipub.</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:187792:67"/> 
               <hi>cauſa:</hi> which Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> could have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſhould have been thus Engliſhed: <hi>An Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsador is an honeſt man ſent to lie abroad for the good of his Countrie.</hi> But the word for <hi>lie</hi> (being the hinge upon which the conceit was to turn) was not ſo expreſſe in <hi>Latin</hi> as would admit (in the hands of an enemy eſpecially) ſo fair a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction as Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> thought in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This coming to the knowledge of K. <hi>James</hi> by the malicious pen of <hi>Caſpar Scioppius,</hi> much offended his Majeſtie: and this cauſed Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi> to write two <hi>Apologies,</hi> one in Latin to <hi>Velſerus,</hi> and another to K. <hi>James:</hi> which were ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, ſo clear, and ſo choicely eloquent, that his Majeſtie (who was a pure Judge of it) could not ſo bear to declare publi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kly, <hi>That Sir H. Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton had commuted ſufficiently for a greater offence.</hi> And now, as broken bones well ſet become ſtronger; ſo Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi> did not only recover, but was much more confirmed in his Majeſties favour.</p>
            <p n="15">15. And his <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſtill increaſed with the Duke <hi>Leonardo Donato:</hi> after whoſe death (as though it had been an entaild love) it was ſtill found living in the ſucceding Dukes, during all the time of his employment to that State; which was almoſt 20 years. All which time he ſtudyed the Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thoſe Dukes, &amp; the Conſultors of State<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wel knowing, that he who negotiates a continual bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs and neglects the <hi>ſtudie of diſpoſitions,</hi> uſually
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:187792:68"/> fails in his propoſed ends: But this Sir <hi>H. Wotton</hi> did not. For by a fine ſorting of fit <hi>Preſents,</hi> curious and not coſtly <hi>entertainments,</hi> alwaies ſweetned by various and pleaſant diſcourſe, by his choice application of ſtories, and his ſo ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant delivery of all theſe, even in their <hi>Italian</hi> Language, he firſt got, and ſtill preſerved ſuch intereſt in the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> that it was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (ſuch was either his <hi>merit</hi> or his <hi>modeſtie)</hi> they never denyed him any <hi>request.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. When he had attended the Emperour and German Princes eight months, to in cline them to equitable conditions for the Reſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation of the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and her Deſcendants to their Patrimonial Inheritance of the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> and had brought the buſineſſe to a probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſucceſſe; but after a victory gotten by the Imperial Army, ſaw the face of peace altered; at his departure from the <hi>Emperour,</hi> he was ſo bold, as humbly to adviſe him <hi>to uſe his Victorie ſoberly, and ſtill put on thoughts of peace.</hi> Which advice though it ſeemed to be ſpoke with ſome paſſion, yet was taken in good part by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who was ever much pleaſed with his cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, all the time that he reſided in his Court; and ſaid, <hi>That though the King his Maſter was lookt on as an Abetter of his enemie the Palsgrave, yet he took him to be a Perſon of much honour and merit, and did therefore deſire him to accept of that</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:187792:68"/> 
               <hi>Jewel, as a teſtimonie of his good opinion of him:</hi> which was a Jewel of Diamonds of more value than a <hi>thouſand pounds.</hi> This was received with all circumſtances and terms of honour by Sir <hi>H. Wotton:</hi> but the next morning at his departing from <hi>Vienna,</hi> at his taking leave of the <hi>Counteſs of Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vina,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Lady, in whoſe houſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mperour had appointed him to be lodged and honourably entertained; <hi>He acknowledged her merits, and beſought her to accept of that Jewel, as a teſtimonie of his gratitude:</hi> preſenting her with the ſame that was given him by the Emperour. Which being ſuddenly diſcovered by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, was by him taken for a high affront, and Sir <hi>H. Wotton</hi> told ſo. To which (in the <hi>nobleneſs</hi> of his mind) he repli'd: <hi>That though he received it with thankfulneſs, yet he found in himſelf an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition to be the better for any gift that came from an Enemie to his Royal Miſtreſſe:</hi> for ſo the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was pleas'd he ſhould call her.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Many other of his <hi>Services</hi> to his Prince and this Nation might be inſiſted on, as his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation of Privileges and courteſies with the <hi>German</hi> Princes and the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> for the Engliſh Merchants, his releaſing and relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many hundred captivated <hi>Engliſh ſoldiers,</hi> and ſending them back in a comfortable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thank God for their lives and libertie, in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:187792:69"/> their own Nation: but I muſt haſt to bring Sir <hi>H. Wotton</hi> in an inſtant from <hi>Venice</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> whither he returned that year in which <hi>K. James</hi> dyed.</p>
            <p n="18">18. The <hi>King</hi> had, for the reward of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein ſervice, promiſed him the reverſion of an <hi>Office,</hi> which was fit to be turned into preſent money, and alſo granted him the Reverſion of the <hi>Maſter of the Rolls</hi> place, if he outlived cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Sir <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> who then poſſeſſed it, and then grown ſo old that he was ſaid to be kept alive, beyond natures courſe, by the <hi>prayers</hi> of thoſe many <hi>poor</hi> which he dayly relieved. Mean while, his condition requir'd preſent ſupport. For in the beginning of theſe imployments he ſold to his elder brother the Lord <hi>Wotton</hi> the <hi>Rent-charge</hi> left by his good Father, and (which is worſe) was now at his return <hi>indebted</hi> to ſeveral perſons, whom he was not able to ſatisfie, but by the <hi>Kings</hi> payment of his <hi>Arrears:</hi> He had brought into <hi>England</hi> many ſervants; of whom ſome were <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Italian Artiſts.</hi> This was part of his condition, who had many times hardly ſufficient to ſupply the occaſions of the day. (For it may by no means be ſaid of his providence, as himſelf ſaid of Sir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi>'s wit, <hi>That it was the very meaſure of congruitie.)</hi> he being alwaies ſo careleſs of mony, as though our Saviours words, <hi>Care not for to morrow,</hi> were to be literally underſtood.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:187792:69"/> 19. But it pleaſed God, that in this juncture of time, the <hi>Provoſtſhip</hi> of his Majeſties College of <hi>Eaton</hi> became void by the death of <hi>Murray,</hi> for which there were (as the place deſerv'd) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny earneſt and powerful Suitors to the King. Sir <hi>Henrie,</hi> who had for many years <hi>rolled the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtone</hi> of a State employment, and knowing experimentally, that the great bleſſing of ſweet content was not to be found in multitudes of men or buſineſſe, and that a <hi>College</hi> was the fitteſt place to nouriſh holy thoughts, and to afford reſt both to his body and mind, which his Age (being now almoſt threeſcore years) ſeemed to require; did therefore uſe his own and the intereſt of all his Friends to procure it. By which means, and quitting the King of his promiſed reverſionary Offices (and by a piece of honeſt policy) he got a grant of it from his Majeſtie.</p>
            <p n="20">20. And this was a fair ſettlement to his mind: but <hi>money</hi> was wanting to furniſh him with thoſe neceſſaries which attend removes and a ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſuch a place. To procure that, he wrote to his old friend Mr <hi>Nicholas Pey</hi> (in whom was a <hi>radicated honeſtie</hi> and true gratitude to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, having been preferd at Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt by the Lord <hi>Wotton)</hi> to uſe all his intereſt to procure five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds of his <hi>Arrears;</hi> for leſſe would not ſettle him at the College, and the want of it <hi>wrinkled his face with cares</hi> ('twas his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion)
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:187792:70"/> and that being procur'd he ſhould the next day after find him in his College, and <hi>Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae remedium</hi> writ over his ſtudy door.</p>
            <p n="21">21. This mony being procured, and he being ſettled according to the deſires of his heart (the College being to his mind as a quiet harbour to a Seafaring man after a tempeſtious voyage) his firſt ſtudy was the <hi>Statutes</hi> of the College: by which he conceiv'd himſelf bound to enter into <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> which he did, being made Deacon with convenient ſpeed. Shortly after, as he came in his <hi>Surplice</hi> from the Church-ſervice, an old friend, a perſon of quality, met him ſo attired, and joyed him: to whom Sir <hi>H. Wotton</hi> replyed, <hi>I thank God and the King, by whoſe goodneſſe I now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m in this condition, a condition which the Emperour Charles the fifth ſeemed to approve, &amp;c. I dayly magnifie my God for this particular mercie of an exemption from buſineſſe, a quiet mind and a liberal maintenance, even in this part of my life, when my Age and infirmities ſeem to ſound me a retreat from the pleaſures of this world, and invite me to contemplation; in which I have ever taken the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt felicitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. After his cuſtomary publick <hi>Devotions,</hi> his uſe was to retire into his Study, and there to ſpend ſome hours in reading the <hi>Bible</hi> and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in Divinity, cloſing up his Meditations with private <hi>prayer.</hi> This was, for the moſt part,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:187792:70"/> his employment in the forenoon. But, when he was once ſate at <hi>Dinner,</hi> then nothing but cheerful thoughts poſſeſs'd his mind, and thoſe ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by conſtant <hi>companie</hi> at his Table ſuch perſons as brought thither additions both of learning and pleaſure. But ſome part of moſt daies was uſually ſpent in <hi>Philoſophical concluſions.</hi> Nor did he forget his innate pleaſure of <hi>Angling;</hi> which he did uſually call, <hi>his idle time, not idly ſpent:</hi> ſaying, <hi>He would rather live five May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>months, than fortie Decembers.</hi> He was a great lover of his neighbors, and a bountiful enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of them very often at his <hi>Table:</hi> where his <hi>meat</hi> was choice, and his <hi>diſcourſe</hi> better.</p>
            <p n="22">22. He was a conſtant <hi>cheriſher</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Youths</hi> in that School, in whom he found etiher a conſtant diligence, or a <hi>genius</hi> that prompted them to learning. For whoſe encouragement he was (beſide many other things of neceſſity and bounty) at the charge of ſetting up in it two rows of <hi>Pillars,</hi> on which he cauſed to be drawn the <hi>pictures</hi> of divers of the moſt famous <hi>Greek and Latin Hiſtorians, Poets and Orators;</hi> perſiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them not to neglect Rhetorick, <hi>Becauſe Almightie God has left mankind Affections to be wrought upon.</hi> And he would often ſay, <hi>That none deſpiſed Eloquence, but ſuch dull Souls as were not capable of it.</hi> He would alſo often make choice of <hi>Obſervations</hi> out of thoſe Hiſtorians and Poets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:187792:71"/> but he would never leave the School without dropping ſome choice Greek or Latin <hi>Apothegm</hi> or Sentence, ſuch as were worthy of a room in the memory of a growing Scholar. He was pleaſed conſtantly to breed up one or more hopely <hi>Youths,</hi> which he picked out of the <hi>School,</hi> and took into his own domeſtick care, and to attend him at his meals: Out of whoſe behaviour and diſcourſe, he gathered obſervations for the better complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his intended work <hi>of Education:</hi> of which, by his ſtill ſtriving to make the whole better, he lived to leave but part of poſterity.</p>
            <p n="23">23. He was a great enemy to wrangling <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes of Religion.</hi> Having in <hi>Rome</hi> made acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with a pleaſant Prieſt, who invited him one evening to hear their <hi>Veſper muſick</hi> at Church; the Prieſt ſeeing Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> ſtand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely in a corner, ſends to him by a boy of the Quire this queſtion writ in a ſmall piece of paper, <hi>Where was your Religion to be found before Luther?</hi> To which queſtion Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> preſently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writ, <hi>My religion was to be found then where yours is not to be found now: in the written word of God.</hi> To another that asked him, <hi>Whether a Papiſt may be ſaved,</hi> he replyed, <hi>You may be ſaved without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that: look to your ſelf.</hi> To another, whoſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe exceeded his knowledge, and was ſtill railing againſt the Papiſts, he gave this advice; <hi>Pray Sir forbear, till you have ſtudied the</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:187792:71"/> 
               <hi>points better: for the wiſe Italians have this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, He that underſtands amiſſe, concludes worſe. And take heed of thinking, the farther you go from the Church of Rome, the nearer you are to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. And to another that ſpake indiſcreet and bitter words againſt <hi>Arminius,</hi> I heard him reply to this purpoſe: <hi>In my travels, I reſted almost a year at Leyden, where I entred into an acquaintance with Arminius, then Profeſſor of Divinitie in that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie, a man much talkt off in this Age, which is made up of oppoſition and contrariety. And indeed, if I mistake not Arminius in bis expreſſions (as ſo weak a brain as mine is may eaſily do) then I know and differ from him in ſome points: Yet, I profeſſe my judgment of him to be, that he was a man of moſt rare learning; and I know him to be of a most ſtrict life, and of a moſt meek ſpirit.—And doubtleſſe many middle witted men (which yet may mean well:) many Scholars that are not in the higheſt Form for learning (which yet may preach well:) do juſtly fall under the reproof of S. Jude, for being buſie-bodies, and for medling with things they underſtand not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25. This is ſome Account both of his Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the Imployment of his time in the <hi>College:</hi> where he ſeemed to have his <hi>Youth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed</hi> by a continual converſation with that <hi>learned Societie,</hi> and a dayly recourſe of other <hi>friends</hi> of choiceſt breeding and parts: by which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:187792:72"/> that great bleſſing of a <hi>cheerful heart</hi> was ſtill maintained, he being alwaies free, even to the laſt of his daies, from that <hi>peeviſhneſſe</hi> which uſually attends <hi>age.</hi> Yet his mirth was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times dampt by the remembrance of divers <hi>old debts:</hi> and finding ſome decaies of health, he did, about two years before his death, that none ſhould be a looſer by it, make his <hi>laſt Will.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which a doubt ſtill remains, whether it diſcovered more <hi>holy wit</hi> or <hi>conſcionable policie:</hi> but there is no doubt, but that his chief deſign was a Chriſtian endeavour, that his debts might be ſatisfied, <hi>(as appeareth by this part of it.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>To my Lords Grace of <hi>Cant:</hi> now being, I leave my <hi>picture of divine love,</hi> rarely copied from one in the Kings Galleries of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation to his Majeſtie: beſeeching him to recieve it as a pledge of my humble reverence to his <hi>great wiſdom.</hi> And to the moſt worthy L. B. of <hi>London,</hi> Lord high Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in true admiration of his <hi>Chriſtian ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie</hi> and contempt of earthly pomp, I leave a <hi>Picture</hi> of <hi>Heraclitus</hi> bewailing, and <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> laughing at the world: moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the ſaid Lo. Archb. his Grace, and the Lo. B. of <hi>London,</hi> of both whoſe favours I have raſted in my life time, to <hi>intercede</hi> with our moſt Gracious Soveraign after my death,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:187792:72"/> in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt, that out of compaſſionate memory of my long ſervices (wherein I more ſtudyed the <hi>publick Honour</hi> than mine own Utility) ſome order may be taken out of my <hi>Arrears</hi> due in the Exchequer for ſatisfection of my <hi>Creditors,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Accordingly, conſcionable ſatisfaction was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for his juſt debts.</p>
            <p n="26">26. He went uſually once a year, if not oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to the beloved <hi>Bocton-hall:</hi> where, he would ſay, he found both <hi>cure</hi> for all cares by the company (which he called the <hi>living furniture)</hi> of that place, and a reſtorative of his <hi>health</hi> by the connaturalneſſe of that which he called his <hi>genial air.</hi> He yearly went alſo to <hi>Oxford:</hi> but the Summer before his death he changed that for a jorney to <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncheſter</hi> College. And as he returned ſaid to his companion: <hi>How uſeful was that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a holy Monk, who perſwaded his friend to perform his cuſtomarie devotions in a conſtant place: becauſe in that place, we uſually meet with thoſe thoughts which poſſeſſed us at our last being there. And I find it thus far experimentally true, that at my now being at that School, ſeeing that verie place where I ſate when I was a boy, occaſioned me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thoſe thoughts of my Youth which then poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="27">27. After his return from <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> he fell into a dangerous <hi>fever</hi> which weakned him much:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:187792:73"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was then alſo much troubled with a continual ſhort <hi>ſpitting;</hi> but that infirmity he ſeemed to overcome in a good degree by leaving <hi>Tobacco,</hi> which he had taken ſomewhat immoderately. And about two months before his death <hi>(Oct.</hi> 1639.) he again fell into a <hi>fever,</hi> which though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſeemed to recover, yet theſe ſtill left him ſo weak, that thoſe common infirmities (which were wont like <hi>civil friends</hi> to <hi>viſit</hi> him, and after ſome ſhort time to <hi>depart)</hi> came both oftner, and at laſt took up their conſtant habitations with him, ſtill weakning his body. In the beginning of a <hi>December</hi> following he fell again into a <hi>Quartane fever;</hi> and in the tenth fit, his better part, that part of Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi> which could not dy, put off mortality, with as much content and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, as humane frailty is capable of, being in perfect peace with God and man.</p>
            <p>His Epitaph by himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hic jacet hujus ſententiae primus Author,</hi> Diſputandi pruritus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccleſiarum ſcabies, <hi>Nomen aliàs quaere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſentence wherein he delighted: <hi>Animas fieri ſapientiores quieſcendo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another, <hi>Amor unit omnia.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Ob. Etonae, Anno Sal.</hi> 1639. <hi>Aetat.</hi> 72.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:73"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:74"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                        <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="biography">
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:187792:74"/>
            <head>VIII. Mr <hi>WILLIAM BEDEL,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Kilmore.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of Mr</hi> Iz: Walton, <hi>and Biſh:</hi> Hall. D. Thomae Carles, Rect. de Barneſley.</head>
            <p n="1">1. WHen King <hi>James</hi> ſent Sr <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi> Embaſſador to the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> he ſent alſo an Embaſſador to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and another to the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> With the Embaſſador of <hi>France</hi> went <hi>Joſeph Hall (late B. of N.)</hi> whoſe many and uſeful <hi>Works</hi> ſpeak his great merit: with the Embaſſador of <hi>Spain, Ja. Wadſworth:</hi> and with Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton, William Bedel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe three <hi>Chaplains</hi> to theſe three Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſdors,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:187792:75"/> were all bred in <hi>one <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> all of <hi>one College,</hi> all Beneficed in <hi>one Dioceſe,</hi> and all moſt dear and entire <hi>friends.</hi> But in <hi>Spain</hi> Mr <hi>Wadſworth</hi> met with <hi>temptations</hi> or reaſons, ſuch as were ſo powerful as to perſwade him (who of the three was formerly obſerved to be the moſt <hi>averſe</hi> to that <hi>Religion</hi> that calls it ſelf <hi>Catholick)</hi> to diſdain himſelf a Member of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and declare himſelf for the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> diſcharging himſelf of his Attendance on the Embaſſador, and betaking himſelf to a <hi>Monaſterial life;</hi> in which he lived very <hi>regularly,</hi> and ſo dyed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When Mr <hi>Hall</hi> came into <hi>England,</hi> he wrote to Mr <hi>Wadſworth</hi> (tis the firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> in his <hi>Decads)</hi> to perſwade his <hi>return,</hi> or the reaſon of his <hi>Apostacie.</hi> The <hi>Letter</hi> ſeemed to have many expreſſions of <hi>love,</hi> and yet there was ſomething in it that was ſo unpleaſant to Mr <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> that he choſe rather to acquaint his old friend Mr <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> with his Motives.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By which means there paſt between Mr <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> and Mr <hi>Wadſworth</hi> very many <hi>Letters,</hi> which be extant <hi>in print,</hi> and did well deſerve it: for in them there ſeems to be a controverſie, not of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> only, but, who ſhould anſwer each other with moſt <hi>love and meekneſſe.</hi> Which I mention the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe it ſeldome falls out ſo in a <hi>Book-war.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Mr <hi>Hall</hi> in an Epiſtle to Mr <hi>Bedel</hi> at <hi>Venice,</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:187792:75"/> having lamented the death of our late <hi>Divines,</hi> addeth: What ſhould this work in us, but an <hi>imitation,</hi> yea (that word is not too big for you) an <hi>emulation</hi> of their worthineſſe? The <hi>Church,</hi> our <hi>Mother,</hi> looks for much at your hands: She knows how <hi>rich</hi> our common <hi>Father</hi> hath left you: She notes your <hi>graces,</hi> your <hi>oportunities,</hi> your <hi>imployments:</hi> She thinks you are gone ſo <hi>far,</hi> like a good <hi>Merchant,</hi> for no ſmall <hi>gain,</hi> and looks you ſhall come home well <hi>laded.</hi> Let me perſwade you to gratifie us at home with the publication of that your exquiſite <hi>Polemical Diſcourſe,</hi> whereto our conference with Mr <hi>Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaſter</hi> gave ſo happy an occaſion. You ſhall hereby <hi>clear</hi> many truths, and <hi>ſatisfie</hi> all Readers: yea I doubt not, but an <hi>Adverſarie,</hi> not too perverſe, ſhall acknowledge the <hi>truths</hi> victory and <hi>Yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. In a <hi>Letter</hi> of Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton</hi>'s to the King, is mentioned a Petition to his Majeſtie from perſons directed hither by the good wiſhes of the <hi>Arch-biſhop of Armagh,</hi> to make Mr <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> (then Reſident upon a ſmall Penefice in <hi>Suffolk)</hi> Governour of <hi>Dublin College</hi> for the good of that Society. And Sir <hi>Henrie</hi> himſelf being required to render ſome <hi>teſtimonie</hi> of Mr <hi>Bedel,</hi> long his Chaplain at <hi>Venice,</hi> in the time of his firſt employment there, goeth on thus:
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:187792:76"/> I am bound in all <hi>conſcience of truth</hi> (ſo far as your Majeſtie will vouchſafe to accept my p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot Judgment) to affirm of him, that I think hardly a <hi>fitter</hi> man for that <hi>charge,</hi> could have been propounded unto your Majeſtie in your whole Kingdom, for ſingular <hi>erudition</hi> and <hi>pietie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie</hi> to the Rites of the Church, and <hi>zeal</hi> to advance the Cauſe of God: wherein his <hi>Travels</hi> abroad were not obſcure, in the time of the excommunication of the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Then he certifies the King: This</hi> is the Man whom <hi>Padre Paulo</hi> took, I may ſay, into his very <hi>ſoul;</hi> with whom he did <hi>communicate</hi> the inwardeſt thoughts of his heart; from whom he profeſſed to have <hi>received</hi> more knowledge in all <hi>Divinitie,</hi> both <hi>Scholaſtical</hi> and <hi>Poſitive,</hi> than from any that he had ever practiſed in his daies. Of which all the paſſages were well known to the <hi>King</hi> your Father of moſt bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>And ſo he concludes in theſe words:</hi> With your Majeſties good favour I end this needleſſe office: for the general fame of his <hi>learning,</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>temper,</hi> and thoſe religious <hi>labours</hi> which himſelf hath Dedicated to your Majeſtie, do better deſcribe him then I am able.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:187792:76"/> 9. Mr <hi>Bedel</hi> was (to the great joy of Sir <hi>Henrie Wotton)</hi> made <hi>Governor</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Colledg:</hi> and, after a fair <hi>diſcharge</hi> of his duty and truſt there, he was thence removed to be <hi>Biſhop of Kilmore.</hi> In both which places, his <hi>life</hi> was ſo holy, as ſeemed to equal the <hi>primitive</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: for, as they, ſo he kept all the <hi>Ember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weeks,</hi> obſerved (beſides his private devotions) the <hi>Canonical hours</hi> of prayer very ſtrictly; and ſo he did all the <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>Faſt-daies</hi> of his Mother the Church of <hi>England:</hi> his <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>charitie</hi> were both ſuch, as ſhewed <hi>his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſet upon things above.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10: Indeed his whole life brought forth <hi>the fruits of the Spirit,</hi> there being in him ſuch a remarkableneſſe, that <hi>he had a good report of thoſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Thoſe that in point of Religion were of the <hi>Roman perſwaſion</hi> (of which there were many in his Dioceſe) did yet ever look upon him with reſpect and reverence; and teſtified it by a concealing and ſafe protecting him, in the late <hi>horrid Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> when the <hi>furie</hi> of the wild <hi>Iriſh</hi> knew no diſtinction of perſons, yet there and then was he protected and cheriſhed by thoſe of a <hi>contrarie</hi> perſwaſion; and there and then he <hi>dyed,</hi> though not by violence.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:187792:77"/> 11. With him were loſt many of his <hi>learned Writings,</hi> which were worthy of preſervation: and, among the reſt, was loſt the <hi>Bible,</hi> which, by many years labour and conference and ſtudy, he had tranſlated into the <hi>Iriſh Tongue,</hi> with an intent to have printed it for publick uſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="portrait">
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187792:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>DE DOMINIS facies hcec eſt, quem Roma cremav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Cur ais<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Auſonium liquerat ille Iovem.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="biography">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:187792:78"/>
            <head>IX. M. <hi>ANT. de DOMINIS,</hi> Dean of <hi>Windſor.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Out of</hi> Dr Barwick. D. Roberto Glyn,, Rect. de Riſington p.</head>
            <p n="1">1. ABout the year 1618. there came over into <hi>England</hi> that very <hi>learned,</hi> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gh <hi>unfortunate</hi> man, <hi>Marcus Antonius de Dominis,</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> Primate of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> &amp;c. Which, (as he was wont to glory,) was St <hi>Hieroms</hi> Native Country, as well as his.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:187792:79"/> 2. This great Scholar, (after he had ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly aſſerted the <hi>truth</hi> of Chriſtian Religion, as it is profeſſed and practiſed in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in ſo many particulars againſt the errors and Corruptions of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> in his Learned and laborious books, <hi>De Republica Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica;</hi> and had alſo from the <hi>Kings</hi> bounty received ſo great incouragements for his honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupports, as the Deanry of <hi>Windſour</hi> and Maſterſhip of the <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy,</hi> beſides many rich and yearly <hi>preſents,</hi> not only from the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> but alſo from the <hi>Nobilitie</hi> and <hi>Gentrie.)</hi> Was ſo far wrought upon by that Polititian <hi>Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Gondamar,</hi> the Spaniſh Embaſſador then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and other inſtruments of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> (that ſought his ruin under ſome ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,) as to take up a reſolution of returning to <hi>Rome;</hi> and could not be diſſwaded from it by his true friends; that really endeavoured hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſecurity. Among whom Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> was neither the leaſt nor laſt, who very earneſtly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him, both by word and writing, not to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelf upon ſuch a hopeleſſe and haſſardous journy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Arch-biſhops pretence was very plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able (and how real he was in it, muſt be left to God,) namely, to negotiate an <hi>unitie in Religion</hi> between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:187792:79"/> and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> upon thoſe moderate grounds which he had laid down, and ſo well defended in his learned and laborious <hi>Works</hi> printed here at <hi>London.</hi> He app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uded himſelf in the excellency of the work, in removing the <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and of the honour in becoming a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairer of the breach,</hi> and of the reward which is promiſed to the <hi>peace makers.</hi> And he thought himſelf the more likely to go through with his work, by reaſon of the ſeaſonable <hi>opportuaitie</hi> he had at that time, when <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fifteenth was newly choſen <hi>Pope</hi> who had been of his old and intimate acquaintance, brought up in the ſame <hi>School</hi> and <hi>College</hi> with him. And however, he was reſolved to make an <hi>attempt;</hi> becauſe if he failed in it, he hoped he ſhould loſe nothing but his <hi>labour;</hi> for as for his <hi>Indemnitie, Count Gondamar</hi> had promiſed him the <hi>ſecuritie</hi> of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> his Maſter. But how well that promiſe was perform'd, will appear by the Sequel.</p>
            <p n="4">4. While he was ſwelled up full with this promiſe and theſe hopes, Dr <hi>Morton</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Lichfield</hi> and <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntrie</hi> coming to viſit him, had this enſuing <hi>diſcourſe</hi> with him, (among many others) which I have often heard him repeat with pleaſure, and ſhall therefore inſert it; and the rather, becauſe it ſhews us of how
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:187792:80"/> little authority the <hi>Council of Trent</hi> would be, if it were not fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the terrour of the <hi>inquiſition.</hi> Leichf. <hi>Domine quid tibi in animo eſt? Anne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertere Papam? Atque etiam conclave papale?</hi> Spal: <hi>Quid ni domine? Anne exiſtimas eos dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſſe, ut non poſſint converti?</hi> Lei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hf: <hi>Minime Domine; nec puto dominum Spalatenſum deum eſſe ut hoc poſſit praeſtare: Noſtin enim concilium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientinum.</hi> Spal. <hi>Novi domine, &amp; auſus ſum tibi dicere, Millies Mille ſunt, etiam in Italia, qui huic concilio fidem nullam adhibeant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. This diſcourſe (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd many other) having paſſed between them, they parted <hi>friendly.</hi> And not long after did this <hi>Biſhop</hi> reinforce his <hi>argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> with an addition of many more, in a long and learned <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to him. Wherein, (among other <hi>Motives</hi> to diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade him from his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourny) he uſed one, wherein he ſhewed himſelf a true <hi>Prophet,</hi> concerning the entertainment he was like to have at Rome. Which proved to be, that before he g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to <hi>Rome</hi> Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fifteenth his old friend, was dead, and a <hi>ſucceſſor</hi> choſen in his pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce; by whom this <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> was <hi>impriſoned</hi> in <hi>Castro St Angelo.</hi> Where he <hi>died,</hi> not without ſtrong <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of murder or poyſon: And his body was afterward <hi>burnt,</hi> (as of an <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick,)</hi> in <hi>Campo Flori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:187792:80"/> 6. I could here ſtart a problematical <hi>queſtion</hi> concerning this learned <hi>Arch biſhop. Whether or no did he ever retract his works, which he puliſhed in print?</hi> If he did, why did they at <hi>Rome</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his body for <hi>Hereſie?</hi> If not, then they abuſed him in his life time, as well as after his de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, in the <hi>manifeſto</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h they put forth in his n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſo learnedly <hi>anſwered</hi> by Dr <hi>Crakanthrop.</hi> There is but one way of avoiding this <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emma,</hi> (and that will bring them into a greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtrait than either of the other,) namely, That <hi>they burnt him after his death for what he retracted in his life time;</hi> and if they own this, they muſt withal proclaim their <hi>unjuſtice</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> to the world. Let them take it in which ſenſe they will, his reaſons and arguments laid down and urged in his <hi>learned works</hi> will more condemn their cauſe than the altering of his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>(ſuppoſing</hi> but not <hi>granting</hi> that he ever altered it,) can tend to their advantage. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is many clear and convincing <hi>Authorities,</hi> from the holy <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>criptures, Councels,</hi> argumentative to any indifferent perſon that is not wilfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt; then his own dubious perhaps impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) authority can countervail.</p>
            <p n="7">7. His <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> (if it was <hi>his)</hi> conſiſteth only in <hi>affirming</hi> or <hi>denying</hi> in bare words: in his <hi>Works,</hi> whatſoever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affirmed or denyed,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:187792:81"/> is <hi>back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> with ſuch convincing and irrefragable <hi>arguments,</hi> as no man hath taken the boldneſſe in above <hi>fortie</hi> years ſince they were written, to undertake the <hi>anſwering</hi> of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="biography">
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:187792:81"/>
            <head>X. Mr <hi>ABRAHAM WHEELOCK.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>D. Tho: Hyde, Biblioth. B. ſuum reddo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THe excellent Mr <hi>Wheelock</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of honeſt plain <hi>Parents</hi> in the Country: by whoſe pious care he was bred up at <hi>School,</hi> till he was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fficiently furniſhed with good learning and ripe years to ſalute the <hi>Univerſitie.</hi> At which time he was ſent to <hi>Kings College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> where he was ſo ſedulous and ſtudious, eſpecially in the <hi>Oriental</hi> Languages, Hebrew, Arabick, Perſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, &amp;c. that he did not ſooner obtain <hi>Degrees</hi> than <hi>Fame,</hi> both in the Univerſity and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> broad.</p>
            <p n="2">2. After he had ſome years enjoyed the Degree of <hi>Master of Arts</hi> in the Unniverſity, Sir <hi>Henrie Spelman,</hi> that rare Antiquary and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:187792:82"/> lover of his Country, did allow to him an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ſtipend of <hi>thirtie pounds,</hi> to explain the <hi>Saxon</hi> Tongue publickly in the Schools: and the Noble Sir <hi>Thomas Adams</hi> Alderman of <hi>London</hi> did, as long as Mr <hi>Wheelock</hi> lived, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly confer u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on him <hi>fortie</hi> pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for the mainte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce of an <hi>Arabick</hi> Lecture, which Mr <hi>Wheelock</hi> likewiſe read publickly. And this they did, not only o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t reſpect, which they owed to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie,</hi> but out of the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat eſteem they had of Mr <hi>Wheelock</hi>'s wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> merits: fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, being aſſured of his great <hi>Abilities,</hi> they thought i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not meet that ſo clear a <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght</hi> ſhould be <hi>hid,</hi> but <hi>ſhine</hi> forth for the common benefit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. After this, in the year 1644, he ſet forth <hi>Venerable Bede</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> in <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> with the addition of his own learned <hi>Notes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thing he attempted was to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te the <hi>Perſian Evangeliſts</hi> into <hi>Latin:</hi> which he performed, and beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to print ſome few ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ters in Perſian and Latin at <hi>London;</hi> whither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was called to be an helper in that great wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of the <hi>Biblia Polyglotta</hi> ſet out by that famous Pillar of learning and religion Dr <hi>Brian Walton,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te L. Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> But Mr <hi>Wheelock</hi> lived only ſo long as to ſee a <hi>Specimen</hi> of the no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entioned <hi>Biblia,</hi> and not any entire part of it publiſhed.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:187792:82"/> 5. Here I muſt not omit, that, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>eminenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> of his learning, and the great <hi>eſteem</hi> he had among perſons of excellent worth, he was of ſuch an <hi>humble</hi> deportment, even to the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of thoſe that addreſſed themſelves unto him, that I think, without prejudice to any other, in this particular he was <hi>the Phaenix of his age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. He dyed at <hi>London,</hi> being about 60 years of age, and lyeth buried in St <hi>Botolphs Church</hi> near Alderſgate.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly adde the <hi>grateful Teſtimonie</hi> of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Waſe</hi> in the Preface to his exact Dictionary: <hi>Clariſs. Dominus Wheelocus, Vir mihi totique Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventuti Cantabrigienſi cum honore memorandus, ut communis Doctor ac Pater; linguae Sax. idem ac Orientalium, imprimis vero Arabicae profeſſor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
